<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vindiciæ revindicate being an answer to Mr. Baxters book intituled Catholick communion doubly defended, by Dr. Owen's vindicator and Richard Baxter, and Mr. Baxter's notions of the saints repentance and displeasure in heaven, considered / by a lover of truth and  peace in sincerity.</title>
            <author>Lover of truth and peace.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65055</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V543</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38022</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17161935</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17161935</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106050</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65055)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106050)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1161:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vindiciæ revindicate being an answer to Mr. Baxters book intituled Catholick communion doubly defended, by Dr. Owen's vindicator and Richard Baxter, and Mr. Baxter's notions of the saints repentance and displeasure in heaven, considered / by a lover of truth and  peace in sincerity.</title>
                  <author>Lover of truth and peace.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Larkin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: preliminary p. [4]</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Catholick communion doubly defended.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Saints.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106050:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106050:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>VINDICIAE REVINDICATAE:</hi> BEING AN ANSWER TO <hi>Mr. Baxters Book,</hi> INTITULED, <hi>Catholick Communion doubly Defended, by Dr.</hi> Owen<hi>'s Vindicator, and</hi> Richard Baxter.</p>
            <p>AND Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Notions OF THE <hi>Saints Repentance</hi> AND Diſpleaſure in Heaven, Conſidered.</p>
            <p>By a Lover of Truth and Peace, in Sincerity.</p>
            <q>Sicut noxium eſt, ſi unitas deſit bonis; ita Pernicioſum eſt, ſi ſit in malis. <bibl>
                  <hi>Greg. mor. Lib. 33.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Non tam Authoritas in Diſputando, quam rationis momenta queren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ſunt. <bibl>
                  <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>George Larkin</hi> at the lower End of <hi>Broad-ſtreet,</hi> next to <hi>London-Wall.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106050:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106050:2"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is none of the buſineſs of this Epiſtle, to beg thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable and <hi>indulgent</hi> Reſpects for the Author and his Work; which is almoſt as <hi>beggarly</hi> as beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Queſtion:</hi> But leaſt of all to crave that thou wouldeſt not be ſo ſuſpicious <hi>and ſevere,</hi> as not to take all Citations by which I repreſent my Author upon my <hi>own</hi> word, without giving thy ſelf the Trouble, and me the ſad Apprehenſions of a <hi>diligent Scrutineer</hi> that will ſee with his <hi>own</hi> Eyes</p>
            <p>I am not much in love with Apologies in Epiſtles to the Reader: But if I muſt in civility treat thee a little that way, it ſhall be only to tell thee, that if I could have found any <hi>particular</hi> faults in the following Tract deſerving thy Cenſure before their Printing off; thou ſhouldest not have found them there. And that I ſuppoſe thou wilt read me as a man liable to <hi>Miſtakes</hi> and Paſſions, of which thy
<pb facs="tcp:106050:3"/>
               <hi>ſelf</hi> art not altogether uncapable; and yet neither nthee nor me to be juſtified.</p>
            <p>As to the Reverend and Learned Author with whom I have here to do, and for whom I have a Veneration for his real worth, and many of his Works ſake: I doubt not but he knows how to put a difference betwixt the Liberty of the Pulpit and the Preſs; and the Countenance of a Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and a <hi>Controverſy.</hi> If this have ſomewhat in the manner that is almoſt <hi>neceſſary</hi> to eaſe my wearineſs in writing, and thine in <hi>reading</hi> it, and I do a little <hi>indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere genio,</hi> pardon me this wrong.</p>
            <p>I intended to have joyned with this Tract, my thoughts of Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Notions of a <hi>Parochial</hi> Aſſembly, being a particular Church organical of Divine Inſtitution, inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant on the Dioceſan; and as ſuch to be Communicated with. But this I have reſerved for a Tract by it ſelf, and 'til I have ſeen Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Anſwer (which I hear is in the Preſs) to a Book intituled, <hi>Mr. Baxters Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Reaſons,</hi> &amp;c. which hath matter in it worthy peruſal, relating to the ſame Argument.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>ERRATA.</hi> Page 9. l. 25. read <hi>in</hi> the Pew. p. 9. l. 36. read <hi>may</hi> go to. p. 17. l. 8. read may <hi>not</hi> be ſaid. p. 31 &amp; 32. for <hi>5th diſpute,</hi> read 5 <hi>Diſputations.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106050:3"/>
            <head>AN ANSVVER TO <hi>Mr. Baxters Book,</hi> INTITULED, <hi>Catholick Communion doubly Defended, by Dr.</hi> Owens <hi>Vindicator, and</hi> Richard Baxter.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. I.</hi> No Conſent of Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> Vindicator to the Catholick Communion defended by Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>I Having read your anſwer to a Book, Intituled, <hi>A VINDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CATION of the late Dr.</hi> Owen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> though I am not <hi>over ſtrongly</hi> addicted to the <hi>Scribling</hi> Humour; yet (Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering all Circumſtances according to my ſmall Prudentials) I was determined (after ſome Heſitations) to a publick reply. And ſome Paſſages in your Anſwer, <hi>look</hi> as if you expected it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Title</hi> of your book in the <hi>Frontiſpiece, Scil. CATHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICK
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106050:4"/>COMM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NION DO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLY DEFENDED, BY DR. OWENS VINDICATOR, AND RICHARD BAXTER:</hi> has ſo much of <hi>Riddle</hi> in it, that, I confeſs, I am not the <hi>Oedipus</hi> who can reconcile it: Nor did that manner of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ign</hi> at the door, direct me to look for an <hi>Anſwer</hi> (much leſs a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ontroverſial Anſwer</hi>) to my Vindication, as the Entertainment <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>thin.</hi> But however <hi>Singular</hi> you have been in miſ-matching the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>le,</hi> and the <hi>Book;</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> Vindicator as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o-authors: I ſhall digeſt them as they come to hand, as well as I can. And in the mean time, You might hold me excuſed, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould in my Title have followed ſo great an Example; only that it be with ſomewhat more of Congruity. But I am not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to make my Reader gaze at ſuch an unuſual Spectacle.</p>
               <p>I have Sir, no light <hi>Quibling</hi> Deſign in this Reply, nor to put <hi>Tricks</hi> upon a Perſon I ſo much Reverence, and in a cauſe ſo <hi>ſerious.</hi> Nor did I expect from the Gravity, and <hi>Sincerity</hi> of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> ſuch a ſtumble at the Threſhold.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>CATHOLICK COMM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NION</hi> are two great words, and in pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in downright Conſtruction, are the epitomy of two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our Chriſtian Creed, the Holy Catholick Church, and the Communion of Saints. And were you as plainly to be underſtood, I muſt acknowledge that, in Intituling me to the <hi>defence</hi> of it, you put an honour upon me, which I am more ambitious, than capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of deſerving.</p>
               <p>But 'tis a hard Caſe, that while we agree herein, and applaud the terms <hi>Catholick Communion;</hi> when you explain your ſence (I think at leaſt that) it goes beyond Catholick Communion: tho' that ſeem a contradiction <hi>in adjecto</hi> by exceſs, as <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick by <hi>defect.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the genuine ſence of Communion, I leave to you, and Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> to beat out, after ſuch a duſt raiſed, wherein 'tis vaniſhed out of ſight. I wiſh you had treated him more calmly, it would have been never the leſs <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> or promotive of <hi>Catholick Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion;</hi> But the <hi>Catholiciſm</hi> of our Communion, you will needs have extending to an actual preſſential joyning with the <hi>Parochial</hi> Aſſemblies, in their Worſhip by the Lyturgy; the Office of the Sacrament of the <hi>Lords Supper</hi> included: yet, not according to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106050:4"/>the National, <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Conſtitution, eſtabliſhed by Law, but as with a particular, divnely inſtituted, and compleat Church, <hi>independant</hi> on the Dioceſan. I am ſure Sir, that the defence of ſuch a Catholick Communion, was none of my intention; and I am as ſure, that you find no ſuch <hi>ſence</hi> in my expreſſions. But if I muſt be for a while <hi>a fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de ſe,</hi> and repreſented as one, who under the pretence of vindicating Dr. <hi>Owen,</hi> have betrayed the cauſe I pretended to defend, by ſiding with his oppoſite in the very Caſe <hi>Controverted;</hi> a little patience will diſcover <hi>another ſcene,</hi> wherein Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and the Vindicator will appear as if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> had forgotten his <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi> and had a priviledge to diſpoſe of me according to his preſent fancy.</p>
               <p>Having gotten over your general Title, I have the proſpect of another, which ſeems to be reſtrained to your <hi>firſt ſection.</hi> And it is, <hi>The Conſent of Dr.</hi> Owens <hi>Vindicator to the Catholick Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on defended by</hi> Richard Baxter.</p>
               <p>Here Sir you make a very hopeful abatement of what you ſtood upon in your <hi>general Title,</hi> there you will have me <hi>defend,</hi> here you come down to <hi>Conſent.</hi> This is at leaſt half a <hi>retractation</hi> at the next word; yet when I have examined what you have to ſhew for the <hi>latter,</hi> it will appear to be a meer ungrounded <hi>Chimaera.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You are pleaſed to diſtribute the <hi>matter</hi> of my Book under <hi>four</hi> heads. I ſhall paſs by the firſt at <hi>preſent,</hi> and conſider the ſecond as moſt proper for me to do in this place; and that you <hi>word</hi> thus.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>Your Conſent to the main of the Cauſe which I defend, and your</hi> diſſent <hi>from the perſons whoſe words I confute: of this I ſhall thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully take notice.</hi> Here is not <hi>Aſſent and Conſent,</hi> but Conſent and <hi>Diſſent.</hi> The laſt was certainly not <hi>Argumentandi,</hi> but <hi>ornandi gratia;</hi> for if I <hi>conſent</hi> to what you <hi>defend,</hi> I muſt needs <hi>diſſent</hi> ſo far from what you Confute; but in <hi>fine,</hi> it will be neither the <hi>one,</hi> nor the <hi>other</hi> in what you expreſs. Yet I muſt obſerve how the Market <hi>falls</hi> from <hi>defend,</hi> to <hi>Conſent to the Catholick Communion, defended by</hi> Richard Baxter. And now 'tis come to <hi>Conſent</hi> to the <hi>main</hi> of the Cauſe which you defend. Yet Sir, though I take no pleaſure in difference, and contradiction; I fear 'tis not yet an agreement.</p>
               <p>Of this <hi>Conſent</hi> you ſay you ſhall thankfully take notice, and accordingly in a few words following, you thank me <hi>again</hi> and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106050:5"/>for the particulars of my aforeſaid Conceſſion, or Conſent. But worthy Sir, conſidering how courtly and friendly you have committed a <hi>rape</hi> upon my ſence and words; and then come off ſo handſome, and ſmoothly with thanks for my Conſent: I call to mind a <hi>much parallel</hi> Caſe, in the Hiſtory of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> by Fryar <hi>Paul</hi> the <hi>Venetian (mihi)</hi> page 322. Lib. 4.</p>
               <p>Chriſtopher Straſſen <hi>one of the Ambaſſadours from the Elector of</hi> Branderburg, a Proteſtant Prince, <hi>to the Council of</hi> Trent; <hi>made a long Oration, ſhewing the good affection and reverence of his Prince toward the Fathers: without</hi> declaring <hi>what his opinion was in point of Religion. The Synod anſwered, (that is the Speaker in its name) That it heard with</hi> great Content, <hi>the Embaſſadours diſcourſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi> in that part, <hi>where that Prince doth</hi> ſubmit <hi>himſelf to the Council, and promiſeth to</hi> obſerve the Decrees.—</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The anſwer which the Council gave was much marvelled at, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the fair and advantagious manner of Contracting, pretending ten</hi> thouſand <hi>by vertue of the promiſe, when the bargain was but of</hi> ten; <hi>for there was no more proportion than between theſe two numbers, in the reverence promiſed by the Elector, and the obedience pretended by the Synod to be given. It was replyed for defence, That the Council did not regard what</hi> was, <hi>but what</hi> ſhould <hi>have been ſaid. And that this is an uſual and pious allurement of the Holy Church of</hi> Rome; <hi>which yielding to the infirmity of her Children, maketh</hi> ſhew to believe <hi>that they have performed their duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to your proofs page 1. you ſay, <hi>That you thank me that I ſay</hi> page 3. <hi>I do not pretend</hi> (in what follows) <hi>to maintain againſt you, that it is unlawful to uſe a Form of Prayer, or comply with an impoſed Lyturgy, or under ſome Circumſtances, to joyn in the uſe of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Neither ſhall I undertake to justify</hi> altogether <hi>the Twelve Arguments you have Printed as Dr.</hi> Owens, <hi>in order to refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I pray Sir compare your <hi>premiſes,</hi> with your <hi>Concluſion.</hi> I do not in <hi>ſuch a Book</hi> maintain ſuch and ſuch things againſt you; <hi>Ergo</hi> I <hi>Conſent</hi> to them, <hi>I defend</hi> them. I can tell you where you have reſented ſuch a groſs fallacy againſt your ſelf very highly. And unleſs you winked hard, and very opportunely; you could not but ſee in my Book ſuch other reaſons given for my not maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe things againſt you in that Book, as would have more then ſufficiently have prevented, or cured you of ſuch a miſtake.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106050:5"/>And you cannot but know that they were in the midſt between thoſe words you cite. For you left out ſeven lines containing thoſe <hi>reaſons,</hi> and then patched together what went <hi>before,</hi> and what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed after the ſaid reaſons, immediately as if it had been my <hi>continued</hi> diſcourſe. But whatever my Sentiments be of the above-ſaid; I ſhall hardly <hi>declare</hi> my aſſent, and conſent to all of them, or the reſt of their fellows; 'till it be to better purpoſe, or by the temptation of a Beneſice.</p>
               <p>You ſay alſo in the ſame page, that you are pleaſed with my expoſition of the Doctors words, and that upon the account of my <hi>reſtrictions</hi> of their ſence. I have no reaſon to be diſpleaſed with this: yet <hi>I</hi> think it very ſit for me to ſay that they will not bear the improvement you make of them, <hi>ſcil. I only here deſire the men and women that have been with me, and profeſt that they thought the Doctors Arguments unanſwerable againſt the lawfulneſs of joyning in the uſe of the Liturgy, to take notice of what his worthy Vindicator ſaith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>I</hi> muſt deſire thoſe perſons to take notice alſo, of what <hi>I</hi> have ſaid, that you think not fit to repeat; and they will find my ſence of <hi>another</hi> Countenance. Some People will take the meer Title Page of ſome anſwers for a <hi>ſufficient</hi> determination, others will look only into the <hi>Anſwerer,</hi> and it may be no further than a few pages or paſſages. If ſuch be miſtaken, let them thank themſelves; <hi>I</hi> ſee 'tis neceſſary to look into what both Parties ſay, let them be who they will: if a <hi>Baxter,</hi> and ſome other men of fame ſo far miſtake.</p>
               <p>But ſo far as your <hi>laſt</hi> paſſage cited, is grounded upon the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction; I</hi> put on the ſenſe of the ſaid Doctors Poſition; It is ſo far from <hi>warranted</hi> thereby, that it is greatly <hi>weakned.</hi> For if that Poſition, and the Arguments be taken with thoſe reſtrictions I ſaid may be put upon them, they are much the more <hi>unanſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> for that.</p>
               <p>You ſay, page 3 <hi>But I think ten to one of the people commonly account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Diſſenters throughout</hi> England <hi>are of my mind, and are for Pariſh-Worſhip rather than either none, or worſe. But by Diſſenters I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you mean thoſe of the Doctors mind, or your own. I</hi> believe Sir, notwithſtanding your thanks for my Charity and Reconciliation, you give in the next words, your Cenſure is too hard, and <hi>uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable,</hi> of thoſe of the Doctors mind, and mine. <hi>I</hi> cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106050:6"/>they ſhould be ſo atheiſtieally or maliciouſly diſpoſed as to chuſe no worſhip or worſe (all circumſtances conſidered) rather than that of the Pariſh. If any adhere to a <hi>worſe</hi> rather than that by <hi>miſtake: I</hi> cannot call that their <hi>Choice.</hi> Dear Sir, <hi>I</hi> wiſh alſo you would either uſe more Accuracy your ſelf (eſpecially in the caſe of Cenſures) or ſorbear exacting it from others, under the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>I</hi> know not how many diſtinctions, to diſcover their confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; though they are well enough underſtood by the willing. <hi>I</hi> beſeech you Sir, who can tell what you mean by <hi>Pariſh-Worſhip?</hi> If all Pariſh Worſhip, <hi>I</hi> believe you are not for it your ſelf rather than none <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc, Scil.</hi> the faults (you ſay) are in the Lyturgy, and more eſpecially in the Offices of Baptiſm and Burial, the bowing at the <hi>pronouncing</hi> the word Jeſus, and toward the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, or the Eaſt. If of ſome <hi>part</hi> of the Pariſh Worſhip, <hi>I</hi> am ſure they are not of <hi>my</hi> mind, or the Doctors either, that will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have none than that, <hi>Scil.</hi> reading the Scriptures Preaching, Prayer, Singing Pſalms. And the Doctor was for Church Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip too (you know) though not for ringing a Bell to proclaim where) whatever it coſt. And you do not ſay rather than <hi>none</hi> more publick or private not Parochial locally, but <hi>ſimply none;</hi> which excludes not only <hi>family</hi> with four added, but ſingle ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worſhip; and all theſe <hi>ad ſemper ex parte poſt.</hi> Yet thus <hi>roughly</hi> am <hi>I</hi> and the Diſſenters of <hi>my mind</hi> repreſented, as contradiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed from thoſe of yours, if <hi>I</hi> take you at the <hi>worſt</hi> your expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions will bear, which <hi>I</hi> am far from, though they inſinuate a great deal too much.</p>
               <p>But now we are come to what <hi>I</hi> told you near the beginning of this Reply; What is become of my <hi>Conſent to,</hi> and <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Communion defended by</hi> Richard Baxter in the Titles? Why, this <hi>Conſent,</hi> and <hi>united</hi> Defence is come to this, in the very <hi>ſame</hi> Caſe, and in the main of it, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> and ten to one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are of <hi>one</hi> mind, and the Doctor and <hi>I</hi> of another.</p>
               <p>Page 3. you repeat a paſſage of min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thus, and you add page 30. <hi>And if (as you allow) the practical determination depends on the</hi> Circumſtances <hi>of the perſons. you reduce the controverſy to a far nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower room than was by</hi> moſt <hi>ſuppoſed: And every one being beſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of underſtanding his</hi> own <hi>Circumſtances, it will not bear great heat and importunity from another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence you interrogate, <hi>But whence cometh thoſe wrong ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106050:6"/>of the moſt) if after twenty years Communion with the Pariſh-Churches, I venture on the Cenſorious ſo far, as to give my reaſons for my own practice, and defend thoſe reaſons, and that practice againſt contrary writings? And ſuch wiſe men as you are ſo reconcileable, and ſee how narrow the Controverſy is; Whence comes it that moſt think it to be what it is not, againſt ſuch frequent plain expreſſions? You and I may conjecture at the cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I muſt acknowledge, and I do it freely, which is more than you had in the Vindication, That I do not hold that worſhiping God by a form of Prayer is <hi>ſimply</hi> unlawful, for the Reaſons I menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, <hi>pag.</hi> 25. ſo that you and I differ not here in <hi>Theſi.</hi> And I alſo declare it my Judgment that thoſe who differ from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (in the caſes controverted) ought not to deal out bitter Cenſures and Reflections for that cauſe: but to maintain brotherly Love, and Evangelical Peace; yea, and <hi>Church Communion too,</hi> ſo far as it may be without ſinful Terms, or notorious Scandal, or what is <hi>rationally</hi> ſuſpected to be ſuch. And I am ſo far from theſe heats and importunities, that (whatever my ſence of your pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice may be) I have been thought, and ſaid to be a kind of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Luke-warm Perſon (if not of your mind) for Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting, and endeavouring to cure a bitter, and <hi>over-hot</hi> Cenſori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs. But Dear Sir, I beg your Excuſe if I anſwer your <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion</hi> as well as I can, I am not dainty to affirm, that all ſides are too guilty of Partiality, and <hi>over-doing.</hi> And you have leſs reaſon to blame thoſe who think the differences very wide and weighty, and <hi>much</hi> greater then you <hi>ſometimes</hi> render it, (For there is a great deal of difference between your High-water, and low-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-mark) when they ſee you ſo much concerned not only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend your own practice, but to reduce others to it; and condemn thoſe who diſſent from you as no <hi>mean</hi> Malefactors, ſtigmatize them as <hi>Separates,</hi> ſuch as unchurch all but themſelves, proud <hi>Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants,</hi> and very bitter <hi>Contemptuous</hi> Language; as if with <hi>Hanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal</hi> your paſſage muſt be made, though with <hi>Fire and Vinegar.</hi> Indeed Sir, your Style is too hard, and heavy for fine work. Love, Reconciliation, and Peace, muſt be fiſhed for with a Calm, not a Storm. What you ſay, page 32. <hi>Humility and Love would conquer: all the World,</hi> is what I have ſaid often, and thought a Thouſand times. It were happy if ſuch Notions were practiced by all that ſeriouſly profeſs Godlineſs, whether they are high or low in <hi>outward</hi> Tranquility: this would Repreſent Chriſtianity in its
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106050:7"/>proper Colours, and turn the Churches ſhame, into the true Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Grace, and Peaceableneſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. II.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hath not proved the Charge of Errors on Dr. <hi>Owen, alias</hi> the Manuſcript, <hi>ſufficiently.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall next Conſider what you ſay, to render my Confutation of your Charge of certain Errors on the Doctor, inſufficient ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing the <hi>Manuſcript</hi> to be his, <hi>as you Printed it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My Conſtruction, and Senſe of the Poſition you diſpute not, but are well ſatisfied with <hi>Expreſly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Page 2. You repeat the firſt Error <hi>Charged</hi> on the Doctor, but (I thank you) you have here reduc'd the ſaid Error to the words and ſence of the Miſtake, though not the Order, and 'tis, <hi>It is not in our Power to make uſe of any part of it,</hi> [the Lyturgy you mean] <hi>as we ſhall think fit.</hi> You add, <hi>and I maintain that, though man hath not put that in our Power, God hath put it in our power to joyn in the good part of tollerable Worſhip, without owning the Faults, (or elſe we muſt joyn with none) you deny not this, page</hi> 27. <hi>but ſay, that he meant it of mans mans giving us Power, (which I never denyed) but it is God that we ſerve.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But if he meant and ſaid it too of the Power or Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty given by man; and I proved it, and conſequently, that the firſt Error you charged him withal was without ground, and your far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcourſe not to the queſtion, as I told you, <hi>page</hi> 27. I had what I pretended to.</p>
               <p>But now you inſiſt on what <hi>you ſay</hi> you maintained, and ſay <hi>I denyed not that.</hi> But Sir, this is another Province. And Reader, if the Reverend Author <hi>miſtakes</hi> as to what he now ſaith he there maintained, and in ſaying I denyed not the ſenſe he gives here, <hi>I</hi> beg his and your pardon, if <hi>I</hi> tranſcribe more then <hi>I</hi> am other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe willing: and <hi>I</hi> ſhall do it fully Word for Word.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> cannot think he bears himſelf upon ſaying <hi>I</hi> denyed it not
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106050:7"/>page 27. It is all one if I denyed it page 28. which I did, if there where any thing like the ſence he intimates; as for the words they are not in the Book I anſwered.</p>
               <p>He ſaith Page 7. in his Anſwer to the Manuſcript, <hi>Though man gives us no ſuch pòwer, God doth; as it is in my power to believe all that one ſpeaketh truly and well, and not that which he ſpeaketh amiſs. I am not bound to own all that any Preacher or Priest ſhall ſay in the Church; God put it into the Diſciples power, to beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, and yet to hear them. Proving all things, is not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving all things.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What is in all this of joyning in the <hi>good part of publick tollerable Worſhip</hi> by a Lyturgy? And how he maintained it by theſe Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which are <hi>nihil ad Rombum,</hi> I cannot imagine, and think my Reader as little.</p>
               <p>The firſt inſtance, <hi>As it is in my power to believe all that one ſaith truly and well,</hi> and not the contrary. I am ſure it is not very ſound as expreſſed, for our power is far ſhort of this; we have not ſuch comprehenſive underſtandings, but our belief may be impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on inevitably by <hi>falſehoods,</hi> in the appearances of truth; elſe our errors were much more culpable then ſometimes they are. And I thought we had been diſputing of <hi>actual joyning in Worſhip,</hi> and not of hearing any aſſertory Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The ſecond inſtance, of what a Preacher or Prieſt ſhall <hi>ſay</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> we are not <hi>bound</hi> to own all that. Do you mean Sir, in Preaching or Praying in the Pulpit, or the Reading Pew? 'Tis all in the <hi>Church,</hi> and 'tis all ſaying. I am herein of your mind Sir; but if you intend it of the <hi>Liturgy read</hi> there, 'tis but <hi>idem per idem;</hi> it is in your power or liberty not to joyn in all, becauſe you are not <hi>bound</hi> to joyn in all. You will not take ſuch Logick for good Coin from an Antagoniſt.</p>
               <p>Third Inſtance, <hi>God put it in the Diſciples power to beware of the Leaven of the Phariſees, and yet to hear them.</hi> This the Text tells you <hi>plainly</hi> to be mean of their falſe Doctrine they Preached, not of their Liturgy for Prayer and Praiſe; and you ſay, Chriſt bid <hi>hear</hi> them; would you have us go to the Liturgy only to <hi>hear</hi> it, or only as we ſhould go to a Sermon? and not worſhip by it? And if we may take your own opinion in the matter, 'tis doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful whether they had any <hi>Liturgy;</hi> or if they had, it was a Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture one; certainly here was no bad leaven in <hi>that.</hi> But of this more hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106050:8"/>Your <hi>4th</hi> Argument or Inſtance, <hi>Proving all things, is not approving all things, is ejuſdem ſarinae,</hi> and deviates from the queſtion <hi>toto Caelo.</hi> Though proving of pretended truth, brought into the Church, be a duty; and holding fiſh that which is good, is to be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent practice: Yet Sir, this concerns primarily the <hi>Credenda.</hi> But ſuppoſe it reach alſo to the <hi>facienda;</hi> it is as little to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For a ſtinted Printed Publiſhed Liturgy, may and ought to be <hi>proved</hi> before it be uſed in <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and not like <hi>Sauls Armour</hi> clapt on <hi>Davids back</hi> to ſight in before he had <hi>proved</hi> it. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly Sir, you would not have people attend to the Worſhip by the Liturgy, in the Pariſh Aſſembly, and inſtead of having their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and devotions ſtirred up, and carried on to God by the Liturgy, to be putting the ſcruple to their Conſciences, whether they are Praying or Sinning. This proof ſhould be made before they come <hi>there,</hi> which they may do at home when they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to do, and not remain a matter of <hi>doubt</hi> when it might before hand have been put <hi>out</hi> of doubt. I <hi>hope,</hi> nay I am <hi>ſure,</hi> that you approve not the practice of many Miniſters, who gave their <hi>aſſent and conſent</hi> to the Liturgy on black <hi>Barth.</hi> (a day to be remembred) before ever they had ſeen ſo much as the <hi>firſt leaf</hi> of it; nor could, becauſe it came not out <hi>time enough.</hi> This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>before</hi> uſing in Worſhip, you commended once as an <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage</hi> of a <hi>ſtinted</hi> form, which Miniſterial, conceived, <hi>extempore Prayer</hi> hath not, but that's <hi>forgotten</hi> here.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>In the ſame page, and next words you add; <hi>You ſay,</hi> when men pray, they bid us pray—In extempore Prayer, both are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to what is good;</q> and then reply, <hi>True: And I may joyn with the good of an extempore Prayer, without owning any evil in it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is <hi>Alexander</hi>-like; cut the knot you cannot, or <hi>will not</hi> untie. Rather than allow me to ſpeak argument or ſence; you will mangle a ſentence ſo, as <hi>I</hi> never met with any do the like before, <hi>I</hi> mean a good man and a good Schollar. <hi>When men pray,</hi> they bid us pray, what then? <hi>in extempore Prayer, both are requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to what is good;</hi> both what? <hi>I</hi> aſſure you <hi>Reader,</hi> my Author will not help you to make it ſence, if you rifle over his whole anſwer for it. But ſeeing my whole ſentence is but <hi>ſhort,</hi> take it intire to a <hi>letter</hi> as my Author had it <hi>in my Book.</hi> 
                  <q>When men Preach, they bid us <hi>hear,</hi> and <hi>the ear tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s words:</hi> but when they pray, they bid us pray. And by the Liturgy our <hi>Amen</hi> is required, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106050:8"/>not our Opinion or Scrutiny: <hi>In extempore Prayer</hi> both are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired to what is good;</q> Now <hi>I</hi> will truſt my Reader to find out the <hi>ſence</hi> and the <hi>reaſon</hi> too. And though <hi>I</hi> can forgive my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor a <hi>thouſand</hi> ſuch wrongs, <hi>I</hi> muſt not excuſe them. As to my Authors reply, 'tis by Conceſſion <hi>True;</hi> and by <hi>repetition</hi> of what was to be proved, which is <hi>instar nihilli.</hi> Now to my Author again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In</hi> the next lines you ſay, <hi>indeed you ſay page</hi> 28. [<q>The Maſs is not more twiſted in all the parts of it by Law, than the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy; nor left leſs to our power to pick and <hi>chuſe.</hi> If this union do render the far greater pollutions, the Hereſy and <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the Maſs infections to the <hi>whole Worſhip:</hi> who can prove that the pollutions of other worſhip, when we are likewiſe commanded not to diſtinguiſh, or divide; doth not in their degree and kind, diffuſe the taint <hi>alike.</hi>
                  </q>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> thank you Sir, for quoting thus much fairly, which yet ſeems to come not <hi>very freely;</hi> yet a good part of the Argument is left <hi>behind,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> ſhall take leave to add a ſnip of it more, which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the very next words [<q>Mental dividing or culling by ſecret diſapprobation, and not joyning in our <hi>hearts,</hi> is all you pretend to; unleſs you did allow (which you do not determine) Mr. <hi>Humphrey Fens</hi> manner to ſay a <hi>loud Amen</hi> to every Prayer of the Liturgy, except the Prayer for the Biſhops, and to that to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by a ſingular ſilence.</q>] Now Sir, inſtead of anſwering my ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, you fall to making a Profeſſion what <hi>you</hi> will do in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral caſes; but at laſt you venture to ſay, <hi>It is not the Conjunction, but the kind of the thing that maketh it unlawful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do you not here roul <hi>Siſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>phus's</hi> ſtone? The Argument returns upon you again [<q>There are good things in the Maſs, yea, good Prayers directed to God only by Jeſus Chriſt</q>] ſhall we therefore go to Maſs, and fall a picking and <hi>culling</hi> in our <hi>minds,</hi> and all is well?</p>
               <p>You tell us not what kind of things in Conjunction make it un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, although <hi>I</hi> put you upon it page 29. of my Vindication in theſe words (but <hi>I</hi> did but <hi>ſurdo narrare</hi>) <q>Nor have you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that no other ſin but <hi>Idolatry</hi> and Hereſy may juſtifie refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to worſhip by the Maſs; nor that far leſs ſins than they may not do it: Nor that the Liturgy hath not (ſome way or other) ſuch ſin cleaving to it,</q> as is like the Leproſy, that could not be <hi>ſcraped, waſhed,</hi> or <hi>fired</hi> ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106050:9"/>Now Sir, <hi>I</hi> pray ſpeak out; and give us leave to go to Maſs, (if that be required, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhould comply with it (which God forbid) with your mental diſtinctions; or tell us what ſins twiſted and mingled with a Worſhip may render joyning therewith unlawful.</p>
               <p>But to be more faithful to <hi>your</hi> reaſonings, than you have been to <hi>mine; I</hi> ſhall recite, and examine them without picking and culling at all; much leſs to your <hi>diſadvantage;</hi> only <hi>I</hi> ſhall tell my Reader by the way, that amongſt all your <hi>ſuperabundart</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions, you give us not one that will include the <hi>kinds</hi> of the things joyned in a <hi>mode</hi> of worſhip, that make it unlawful to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>excluſive</hi> of thoſe which do not, or that <hi>look like it;</hi> and ſo you leave us as you found us. Let us examine what you have done; 'tis in page 2.</p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>God is the maſter of his Worſhip;</hi> very right! And 'twere well if there were no more. <hi>I do what he bids me, though man contradict it.</hi> This is much better, becauſe practical. But ſhall we take it for an anſwer to my argument? (as you call it) your anſwer is of doing what <hi>God</hi> bids you, tho <hi>man</hi> contradict it: the queſtion is, of doing what <hi>man</hi> commands, mixed inſeparably with what <hi>God</hi> contradicts. Take it at the beſt as to the queſtion, it is but this: <hi>I</hi> will go to Liturgy, to Maſs (for that is the queſtion) and joyn in that part which God requires (let it be mixed with what it will) whatever men ſay to the contrary. This is the plain ſence of your anſwer. But <hi>I</hi> believe far better things of you; you explain <hi>your ſelf</hi> thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If God bid me hear, and believe the Scriptures, and man ſay hear alſo, and believe the Apocrypha. I will openly profeſs I obey God, and you no further than you contradict not God.</hi> All this is good, but not in this place, becauſe <hi>impertinent.</hi> What are we the wiſer for it? What is that to the queſtion? What you will profeſs in ſuch a caſe? Tell us what you will do, in the caſe before us, and give us a reaſon for't too. What man that would but be thought to fear God, would not profeſs ſuch a general <hi>dangerleſs Profeſſion</hi> in <hi>high Change,</hi> in a Popiſh Countrey? Yet he will hardly merit the Chair in <hi>this debate,</hi> for ſuch a reſolution.</p>
               <p>You proceed, Rather <hi>than not hear the Scriptures,</hi> I <hi>will hear alſo the Apocripha, but not believe it to be Gods Word. But if they bid me hear the Alcoram alſo, I will withdraw.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:106050:9"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What this is to the Purpoſe, I cannot tell. If you will do this, and much more; the Queſtion ſtands juſt where it did, excepting only the <hi>Authority</hi> of your inclination or <hi>Example.</hi> But if the Rectitude of what you ſay you <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>will not,</hi> may be exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, <hi>I</hi> may ask you,</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. What neceſſity there is, that you ſhould hear the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> or not hear the Scripture?</item>
                  <item>2. Whether you mean that you will rather hear the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> read, as a part of Gods <hi>Worship,</hi> rather than forbear to hear the Scripture read, with other Concommitants in the Lyturgy, at the ſame time, and place?</item>
                  <item>3. Though in the mean time, you believe not the <hi>Apocrypha</hi> to be Gods Word: Do you believe that 'tis not intended it ſhould be believed to be Gods Word? or inſinuated to be ſo?</item>
                  <item>4. If any <hi>other</hi> writing, no more <hi>Gods word</hi> than the <hi>Apochry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pha,</hi> and containing matter as lyable to Exception, and ſtanding as <hi>Candidates</hi> for the honour of Gods word; ſhould be <hi>joyned</hi> to the Scripture, and read <hi>juſt</hi> in the manner as <hi>they</hi> are, bearing their part in Gods Worſhip. (for Inſtance, The works of <hi>Seneca</hi> Hiſtory of the Nine Worthies, Popiſh <hi>Legenda,</hi> of their Saints Miracles, <hi>Aeſops</hi> Fables,) Would you rather joyn in <hi>this</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, with your <hi>mental</hi> Reſervations and <hi>Distinctions,</hi> then forbear or with-draw?</item>
                  <item>Laſtly, If there be not <hi>ſome,</hi> yea <hi>many</hi> things in the Alcoran, as <hi>true,</hi> and as good as many things in the <hi>Apocrypha?</hi> And not <hi>many</hi> things more falſe and worſe in the Alcoran, than <hi>ſome</hi> things in the <hi>Apochrypha?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>And if the Books fore-mentioned, may not claim a <hi>Parity? Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dith, Bet</hi> and the <hi>Dragon, Tobit,</hi> with the Hiſtory, <hi>Legends,</hi> and <hi>Fables?</hi> When all theſe Queries are reſolved, which ſtand as fair for your Embraces as what you aſſent unto, we may the better underſtand <hi>you,</hi> but not the Queſtion.</p>
               <p>Next you ſay ſomewhat in room of a Proof, <hi>That it is not the Conjunction, but the kind of the thing that maketh it</hi> [the Worſhip] <hi>unlawful,</hi> viz. <hi>An honeſt weak man, an Antinomian, an Anabaptiſt, a Presbyterian, or whoever you diſſent from in tollerable caſes, may mix his opinion, and faulty Expreſſions and Methods with his Prayer and Scrmen; as intimately as evil is mixt in the Moſs; and yet you will not refuſe Communion with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106050:10"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All you aim at by this, is but <hi>argumentum ad hominem,</hi> and ſuch a one too, as is but <hi>a facto ad jus:</hi> but here is neither. The Caſe with that in Queſtion is, <hi>impar &amp; Congreſſus.</hi> 'Tis true, if what yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſay of me here be true; that I do not reject Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion for ſuch kind of Faults in the <hi>Adminiſtrator</hi> of the Worſhip and his Adminiſtration: and I will allow you <hi>that</hi> as eaſily, as that a man muſt not put away his Wife for <hi>every</hi> fault: But yet I muſt add, that you put the Caſe <hi>ill,</hi> and ſtrain it off the Tenters, to make it reach <hi>yours.</hi> For, there <hi>may</hi> be ſuch faults mixed, doth not reach to <hi>there is,</hi> there <hi>muſt</hi> be, there <hi>ſhall</hi> be ſuch faults; which you know is ſaid of the <hi>Lyturgy,</hi> by them you <hi>oppoſe.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the faults in a <hi>Sermon</hi> are not <hi>ad rem,</hi> much leſs <hi>ad idem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor are they that concern the more direct Worſhip, as Prayer and Praiſes, as <hi>intimately mixt</hi> as in the Maſs; which you pleaſe to inſtance in to make the worſt on't, or our Lyturgy either, as to what faults are in the matter; for they are not <hi>impoſed</hi> on <hi>us</hi> to hear and worſhip by, either by <hi>Law,</hi> nor as neceſſary terms of Communion, nor are they <hi>all</hi> juſtified as no <hi>faults,</hi> nor are they <hi>bound</hi> to commit them by <hi>Law,</hi> nor are they known to us <hi>before</hi> we joyn, that ſuch faults will be; (except what common infirmities may infer) nor are they <hi>perpetuated</hi> by a Law, nor is it a <hi>Crime,</hi> much leſs a <hi>Penal,</hi> a capital one, to <hi>Reform</hi> them, to adviſe of, yea reprove them for ſuch faults. (Except the Errors of Opinion) they are confeſſed to be faults <hi>particularly,</hi> be wailed as their <hi>Sin and Burden.</hi> And they pray and endeavour to do their work for <hi>matter</hi> and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Expreſſion</hi> with <hi>greater</hi> Perfection: This may be ſaid of the <hi>honeſt</hi> that yet are E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous and weak. But tell me of one of our Miniſters of the Lyturgy that doth, or dare make publick Confeſſion, of one fault in matter or form in the Lyturgy; and pray to God to Reform it, and help them to do it better? or where doth the Lyturgy direct o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch a Confeſſion and Prayer? And yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the whole of <hi>neceſſary legal Miniſtry,</hi> with one of the <hi>Homilies</hi> added once in a <hi>long</hi> while.</p>
               <p>But Sir, you might have remembred what I ſaid, <q>Page 29. (but it was not for your turn) There is no Pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y in a Word or Sentence, exceptionable in a Conceived Prayer <hi>extempore,</hi> with the Lyturgy in its <hi>intire</hi> form, with all known or <hi>doubtful</hi> Circumſtances. Many may be ſound who in Conceived <hi>extem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore</hi> Prayer, do not pollute them with failings in the <hi>matter;</hi>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106050:10"/>and others that have Errors in their <hi>minds,</hi> do not put them into the <hi>Words</hi> of their Prayers.</q> So that Communion with theſe more able Orthodox men, is nothing ſo <hi>dangerous,</hi> nor lyable to your <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There remains one thing more, in which you ſum up your <hi>ſence</hi> of you Argumentations in this Paragraph, and it is by a <hi>Similitude</hi> which proves <hi>nothing.</hi> But if it may help us to underſtand your <hi>meaning,</hi> I will not <hi>Envy</hi> my Reader the ſight of it. <hi>It is lawful</hi> (ſay you) <hi>to drink beer that hath bad water mixt, rather than none: But not to drink that which hath Poyſon equally mixt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Here is a <hi>Ratheriſm,</hi> and a down-right Negative. The firſt (if I can underſtand you) is meant of our <hi>Lyturgy,</hi> the latter of the Popiſh Maſs. But to follow your Similitude, muſt one of theſe be our Election? muſt we take this <hi>bad</hi> mixture, or not drink <hi>at all,</hi> and conſequently die of a <hi>ſullen Humour,</hi> or a Pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>more</hi> nice than <hi>wiſe?</hi> You can tell a better way than <hi>either;</hi> and that is, to drink that which is more pure, wholſom, and <hi>reliſhable,</hi> if it may be had for Love or <hi>Money.</hi> And you believe Sir, <hi>they</hi> may have <hi>better</hi> that will but go to the <hi>Coſt</hi> on't, though ſometimes you expreſs <hi>Peters</hi> pity, <hi>Be it far from thee, this ſhall not be unto thee,</hi> Mat. 16.23. And you know what thanks he had for it from his Maſter.</p>
               <p>For the latter, you are <hi>more out,</hi> or more <hi>ſhort,</hi> or <hi>both.</hi> It is not <hi>lawful to drink that which hath Poyſon</hi> equally <hi>mixt:</hi> you are more <hi>out,</hi> becauſe 'tis <hi>leſs</hi> to the <hi>Purpoſe.</hi> Remember Sir, you are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that 'tis the the kind that's in Conjunction, which makes the Worſhip <hi>unlawful;</hi> and now you are come from the <hi>quale</hi> to the <hi>quantum;</hi> and in <hi>truth</hi> to <hi>both:</hi> Poyſon, the <hi>quale,</hi> equally mixt, the <hi>quantum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I ſaid alſo that 'tis more <hi>ſhort,</hi> 'tis proveable <hi>enough;</hi> for ſhould we take no better <hi>heed,</hi> than to your <hi>Direction,</hi> we were in the Eyes of all Men (and your own too, when you look on this Paſſage again) utterly <hi>undone.</hi> May we drink <hi>Poyſon,</hi> ſo there be not full as much Poyſon as better Liquor in the Draught; or any Poyſon at all? I know Sir, though you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded it thus <hi>unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily,</hi> your <hi>meaning</hi> is ſtill; we may go to the Lyturgy, rather then to the Maſs. And I am ſo far of your mind, but as to what you have yet ſaid, <hi>reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at Probandum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You proceed and ſay, To <hi>page</hi> 29. of my Vindication, <hi>I think if
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:106050:11"/>a</hi> Turk <hi>pray againſt Idolatry, Murder,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that Prayer is materially good; But as to goodneſs from a holy Principle, no Hypocrites is good.</hi> You had ſaid in your Anſwer to the Manuſcript, page 7. <hi>Heathens and Turks have good Prayers,</hi> but may we joyn with them? you have not told us why not; but only in Caſe of their being twiſted with <hi>ſuch</hi> Hereſie and Idolatry. <q>But I had denyed Heathens and Turks having <hi>good</hi> Prayers, becauſe without Faith in Chriſt, though they may be Prayers for ſome good thing.</q> This Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine you cannot bear, it being in Contradiction to what had paſt the <hi>Warranty</hi> of your Pen; but you will bring it over to another Tryal, and you <hi>will ſay</hi> they may be materially good; <hi>I</hi> ſaid ſo <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,</hi> but that does not ſo well like you; but being for the <hi>matter</hi> good, they muſt be <hi>good Prayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will put you a few Caſes, to ſee how your <hi>Rule</hi> looks. Suppoſe a man utter the matter of a good Petition in Sport, or Deriſion of Religion, as has been ſometimes in <hi>Playes;</hi> are they good Prayers? Conjuring ſhall have good Prayers too, by this Rule; for ſometimes it contains ſome matter of Petition for good. The Heathen prayed to <hi>Bacchus</hi> for a good Vintage, to <hi>Ceres</hi> for a good <hi>Harvest;</hi> The matter of their Prayers were good, though directed to Idols; but by your Rule theſe are to be juſtified as <hi>good</hi> Prayers. How dear is ſelf defence! that will not permit an Eminent Chriſtian Divine, to allow that there can be no good Prayers with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Faith in Christ,</hi> but it muſt be <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> out of doors, to ſave the Turks and Heathens <hi>good Prayers;</hi> becauſe he had unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly ſaid, <hi>they</hi> had good Prayers.</p>
               <p>You Conclude this Argument ſaying, <hi>The Inſufficiency of my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer you no way manifeſt, 'till you prove that I muſt joyn with all that is in publick Worship, or with none.</hi> If ſo, your Anſwer is <hi>unan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable;</hi> but though <hi>I</hi> attempt no ſuch <hi>impoſſible</hi> things, <hi>I</hi> will be content to ſtand to the Readers Judgment (that doth not allow a <hi>name</hi> to weigh <hi>too</hi> much) if your Anſwer be not <hi>apparently</hi> inſufficient.</p>
               <p>Yet Sir, beſide what I have already ſaid to <hi>difference</hi> the faults of the Worſhip <hi>I</hi> have deſcribed; and that other Worſhip you will bring under the <hi>ſame</hi> difficulty; <hi>I</hi> will add, that where Worſhip is according to <hi>Divine Inſtitution.</hi> (which doth not ſuppoſe <hi>them</hi> obliged by it to be <hi>Angels,</hi> but men, men ſubject to <hi>Infirmities</hi>) And theſe men do <hi>Profeſs</hi> ſo far as they have <hi>attained,</hi> to walk by
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106050:11"/>the rule of <hi>Gods Word,</hi> and to reform, and riſe to a nearer Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to the Divine Rule, as they ſhall be able to <hi>underſtand</hi> it: And their Worſhip contains <hi>nothing</hi> in it, either by <hi>exceſs or defect,</hi> which excludes the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of Chriſtian Worſhip, <hi>accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> to God through Chriſt, when tendred in <hi>Sincerity.</hi> I believe theſe may be joyned with, without <hi>partaking</hi> with their Sins in Worſhip; while I am not immediately guilty of the <hi>ſame</hi> Sins. This may be ſaid of the fore-deſcribed? And worthy Sir, I know not by what <hi>other</hi> medium to ſet up a Fence againſt the moſt <hi>polluted</hi> Worſhip in the <hi>World,</hi> that hath ſomewhat good in it, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending God the Object. When <hi>Temptation</hi> is at the door, meer <hi>mental Diſtinctions</hi> will undo all, and betray Religion <hi>Peice-meal.</hi> If you, or any other can inſtruct me better, <hi>I</hi> ſhall be thankful for it. In the mean time, <hi>I</hi> am well content with what <hi>I</hi> have ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. III.</hi> The Remains of what Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith in his Defence, againſt my Diſcharge of Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> pretended Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, Conſidered.</head>
               <p>SIR, The Doctor, ſo far as concerned in the <hi>firſt</hi> Error by you charged on him, being after ſo large an Encounter <hi>Revindicated.</hi> You making me little to do, and next to <hi>nothing,</hi> about all the reſt, you have ſpared me much farther travail in that Province. I hear no more of your Proof of the other ſeven or eight which <hi>I</hi> defended, to be the Doctors Errors, or any Bodies elſe, except in two Paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which <hi>I</hi> ſhall alſo Conſider.</p>
               <p>You ſay, page 27. <hi>Some other Practical Doctrines we differ about,</hi> as where you report me to <hi>ſay,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Page</hi> 30. [<hi>I</hi> doubt not to affirm, that doing that which a <hi>Law</hi> requires, ſo far as the <hi>Intention</hi> is moved by the Law, is a <hi>juſtifying</hi> of it. And ſubmitting to <hi>any Law,</hi> upon the Conſideration of its <hi>Penalties,</hi> is ſo far a juſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106050:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>its <hi>preceptive</hi> part, as not ſo <hi>great</hi> an Evil as its <hi>Penal.</hi>]</q>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe two Sentences, you charge with <hi>two</hi> faults. The firſt of a Defect in <hi>Limitation,</hi> the ſecond of a Defect in Limitation and <hi>Distinction.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Sir, (if <hi>juſt</hi>) are a great <hi>Abatement</hi> of that <hi>bad</hi> Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance you put upon the ſuppoſed Error (which <hi>I defend</hi>) in your Anſwer to the Manuſcript, <hi>Page</hi> 7. viz. <hi>That our Communion juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth all the Laws that impoſe the Lyturgy; yea the Penal Severities: This is too groſs an Error to be defended, with any ſhew of Proof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Before you fall to the Proof of my foreſaid Defects in the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> you except againſt another Paſſage of mine in your <hi>Way;</hi> which <hi>I</hi> ſhall take out of the <hi>way,</hi> before <hi>I</hi> deal with the others: 'tis this, ['None that <hi>I</hi> know of ſay it, [Communion in the Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy] is a Duty <hi>ſimply,</hi> or without any Dependance on <hi>humane</hi> Sanction.] Your Deſign in <hi>this</hi> exception ſeems to me, to prevent or ſence your ſelf againſt ſuch Objections as might be made againſt your <hi>own Practice,</hi> which was not to hold <hi>this Communion,</hi> when the Sanction of the Law lay (at leaſt) aſleep. But Reverend Sir, if that be it; <hi>I</hi> ſhall lay, that 'tis little my Buſineſs, or inclination to Cenſure, or <hi>judge</hi> my Brother in doubtful Controverted mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. <hi>To his own Maſter he ſtandeth or ſalleth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had you told me of any one Perſon, Author or other, that ſays 'tis a Duty <hi>ſimply,</hi> it had been ſomewhat <hi>like</hi> a Conviction of my ſaying to be culpable: But all you ſay, is what <hi>your ſelf</hi> have ſaid, and <hi>practiced,</hi> which no way <hi>Contradicts</hi> me neither. You ſay, <hi>I have largely told you, that I take it to to be a Duty to hold ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion where no better at leaſt is;—And that it is in Obedience to Gods Commands, more than mens, that I have gone to the Pariſh-Churches;</hi> And would have <hi>gone as much if the Law had not Commanded it, but only deprived me of better.</hi> But Sir, is that a Duty <hi>ſimply</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that is obliged to, <hi>only</hi> by that great <hi>ſtrait,</hi> no better is to be had; Worſhip God <hi>thus,</hi> or not at all? Or is <hi>that</hi> no Dependance on <hi>humane</hi> Sanction, which depends not only on the Laws (not <hi>forbidding</hi>) but depriving you of better? <hi>I</hi> think the Sanction of the Law goes a great way, where it not only commands, but actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and effectually deſtroyes all other ways, but that which it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes. <hi>I</hi> wonder none of our modern wits and men of the times, in Preſs or Pulpit, have ever yet found in their hearts to ſay? that 'tis <hi>ſimply</hi> a Duty, and thereby we are obliged to it in.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106050:12"/>Conſcience toward <hi>God,</hi> without the <hi>medium</hi> of the Magiſtrates Command or <hi>Compulſion.</hi> Little we hear from them but Law, Law, <hi>Jupiter &amp; Fulmina.</hi> You might have ſpared me, and your ſelf this Trouble, had you not been offended at your <hi>own Shadow.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for my defective <hi>Limitation,</hi> you ſay; <hi>But as to your</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted <hi>Affirmation, I am as much</hi> poſt doubt <hi>that it is not true, as you</hi> unlimitedly <hi>expreſs it. The intention may be moved by a Law for the</hi> Effects <hi>or</hi> Conſequents <hi>ſake; and not juſtifie the Law, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly juſtifie the Act of the Subject. Yea it may be moved by the formal Authority of the</hi> Lawgiver, <hi>expreſt by the Law; and yet not juſtifie the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How happily have I ſped in this Argument! to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing Objected but a little waiſt of <hi>Accuracy,</hi> which the beſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may ſometimes be charged with.</p>
               <p>Truly Sir, when I wrote what you ſo <hi>confidently</hi> Contradict, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs I had <hi>limited</hi> it: I did not think of a Lecture of <hi>Juris-prudence.</hi> I wrote that which concerned <hi>Common</hi> people to underſtand; and I <hi>doubt not ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> to ſay, that I wrote <hi>Common Sence,</hi> and I was very well <hi>underſtood,</hi> though I did not trouble them with <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rther</hi> Limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. But Sir, was not that a Limitation ſufficient, [<hi>So far</hi> as the <hi>Intention</hi> is moved by the Law.] But you teach me that <hi>the Intent may be moved by a Law, for the Effects or Conſequents ſake, and not juſtifie the Law.</hi> I aſſure you Sir, I have rubbed my <hi>morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> Eyes, and cannot yet ſee the Defect.</p>
               <p>I ſay, that if the intention he moved by the Effects or Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, as ſuch, (<hi>ſimply</hi> as ſuch) though the Law be the <hi>Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> the Intention is not moved by the Law at all. For <hi>ſuch</hi> an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention would not be moved by a Law Conſidered <hi>without</hi> thoſe Effects and Conſequents; and it <hi>would</hi> be moved with <hi>thoſe</hi> Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects and Conſequents, though they had no Relation to a Law at all. Therefore your arguing from the Intention moved by the <hi>Effects</hi> and Conſequents, as not ſufficient to juſtifie the Law, is but making an Argument of your <hi>own</hi> to confute inſtead of <hi>mine.</hi> But let us try if your inſtances will give more light.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Joſeph and Mary were taxed with others, by Auguſt us Law; they were moved by that Law, and its Effects to pay the Tax: yet juſtified not the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> All you can prove is, that they <hi>paid</hi> the Tax, the mere matter of <hi>Fact:</hi> The Text ſpeaks nothing (and therefore you can
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106050:13"/>
                  <hi>prove nothing</hi>) of their <hi>Intention,</hi> or by what it was <hi>moved.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>The Iſraelites might they the Philiſtines that forbad them Smiths and Swords, &amp;c.</hi> How prove you that? and if you prove it, what follows, but an <hi>All</hi>-ſignificant, or an <hi>inſignificant &amp; Catera?</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>When Chriſt ſent Peter to take a Fiſh, with Money in his mouth, and pay Tribute; the Law moved his Intention, becauſe of the Offence that would follow the breaking of it: and yet his Anſwer intimateth that he juſtified not the Law.</hi> Indeed Sir, I wonder at your impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, as if I and your Readers had not <hi>read</hi> the Scripture, nor were Maſters of a grain of <hi>Sence.</hi> The Scripture ſaith <hi>plainly,</hi> that he did it to avoid the <hi>Offence; that</hi> moved this <hi>Intention,</hi> not a word of the Law here. And for his Anſwer, it imported <hi>plainly,</hi> that he would keep his <hi>Sence</hi> to <hi>himſelf,</hi> that he might neither of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend <hi>Caeſar,</hi> nor his Countrey men, nor enſnare <hi>himſelf.</hi> Truly Sir, I am conſtrained to ſpeak plain; half a good Argument is worth all theſe, and an hundred more ſuch. You have a heap be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, of mere <hi>unproved</hi> Dictates, very unworthy of your Pen; The intelligent <hi>wary</hi> Reader will eaſily ſee it: and yet you conclude this Argument, with <hi>Dear Brother I will not aggravate your Error, by its ill Conſequences.</hi> I thank you for your Love, but I need not your Favour in <hi>this</hi> Caſe, unleſs for <hi>their cauſe,</hi> who will take a mans Arguments to be knockt <hi>dead</hi> beyond Redemption, if Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> hold up but a <hi>Straw</hi> at them.</p>
               <p>Somewhat muſt be ſaid to my Defect in the <hi>latter</hi> Sentence; of which you ſay, <hi>And as to your ſecond Information, it is not true without Limitation, that</hi> [<q>Submitting to a Law, on Conſideration of the <hi>Penalties,</hi> is <hi>ſo</hi> far a juſtifying its preceptive part, as not ſo great an evil as the Penal] You ſay, <hi>this is confuſed work,</hi> and why?</q> 
                  <hi>The Preceptive part of the Law, is</hi> actus precipientis, <hi>the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Act. Again, Forgive me for telling you, that you ſhould have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed the</hi> preceptive <hi>part of the Law from the matter</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>by it, and the Evil of the Law and</hi> Law-maker, <hi>from the Evil of the Obeyer.</hi> And what then? <hi>And then have Concluded</hi> only, <hi>that he that obeyeth a Precept only to avoid the Penalty, profeſſeth the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty to be worſe then his Act of Obedience: But he doth not make it worſe then the Law, or the Lawmakers Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Reverend Sir, I am not yet ſo <hi>Learned,</hi> or <hi>ſelf</hi>-conceited, as not to be willing to learn of a far <hi>meaner</hi> Tutor: But ſtill with this Proviſo, that he <hi>inform,</hi> but not <hi>impoſe</hi> on my Underſtanding.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106050:13"/>I could (without great difficulty) have diſtinguiſhed the <hi>pars le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlativa,</hi> from the <hi>actus imperantis,</hi> and that from the <hi>actus impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and all from the <hi>Lex formata,</hi> and ſo on. But <hi>cui bono?</hi> my Reader would have been little the wiſer. Could my Reader <hi>ſo</hi> miſtake, as to <hi>imagine</hi> I meant that the evil of the Penalty was not ſo great as the <hi>Law-makers Sin?</hi> and is not the <hi>actus imperatus,</hi> included in the matter commanded in the <hi>Sence</hi> of the <hi>preceptive</hi> part? And I think, I was diſtinct <hi>enough,</hi> where my Reader might <hi>well</hi> underſtand, and could not by any fault of <hi>mine,</hi> miſs my mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But Sir, whatever Pleaſure you take in it, I take <hi>little,</hi> and (it may be) our Readers none at all, in <hi>this</hi> part of the Debate, wherein we do but <hi>res parvas magno Conatu agitare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You give me <hi>no more</hi> occaſion to contend againſt you, by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering what you oppoſe to my Defence of the Doctors pretended Errors. You remember me of one thing more in the <hi>Polemical</hi> part of my Book, but not by way of <hi>Contradiction,</hi> Scil. Page 32. I ſay, ['Doth he ſay a word of owning Pariſh-churches and Worſhip;] Thus much, and <hi>no</hi> more you repeat of <hi>that</hi> Section. And you An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>If you, or he ſay nothing againſt theſe, we ſhall leave the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan to others. But if you be the man, I have lately privately writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to; I doubt not but I have proved to you, that Pariſh Churches that have good Miniſters, are true particular Churches, and thoſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters true Paſters: and that any Biſhops holding the contrary, doth not diſprove it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Snap</hi> of my Defence <hi>broken off</hi> from its <hi>Fellows,</hi> your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der will underſtand little by, but I ſuppoſe, you only deſigned to bring in by that, what you ſay you wrote <hi>privately:</hi> but I perceive you know not to <hi>whom,</hi> at leaſt whether it were to me, or to ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body <hi>elſe:</hi> However, this Notice is very welcome. As to what you ſay you have <hi>proved,</hi> I do very much doubt it. If I had had the happineſs to have ſeen thoſe <hi>Proofs,</hi> and they had proved con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing to me; you had ſaved me the Labour of agitating <hi>that</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion in a <hi>following</hi> diſcourſe. And I take it to be <hi>ſo much</hi> more worth determining, as it ſeems to be the very <hi>Baſis</hi> of your Zeal for compleat <hi>Parochial</hi> Communion.</p>
               <p>After your Notices of what I had done in Defence of the Manuſcript (which was as much as my <hi>expreſs</hi> deſign, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:106050:14"/>to prove that it was not ſuch a feeble and <hi>groſs</hi> thing as <hi>you</hi> Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented it, (let it be whoſe it would) you obſerve ſome things <hi>page</hi> 4. I have not done. That is, that I have not defended the <hi>reſt</hi> of the Manuſcript. And <hi>page</hi> 5. you thank me for defending <hi>none</hi> of thoſe you innumerate. I take not your thanks <hi>amiſs,</hi> tho' I had other Reaſons for not doing it, then ſuch as it may be you <hi>Suppoſe;</hi> yet ſuch as may be eaſily ſuppoſed, if you <hi>pleaſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And not to ſuffer you to be grateful <hi>alone, I</hi> thank you alſo, that you ſaid ſo <hi>little</hi> to defend your charge of the firſt Error you charged on the Doctor, or Manuſcript, and that you ſaid <hi>leſs</hi> to the ſecond, and nothing at all to all the reſt (ſix or ſeven in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber) which I diſcharged from <hi>that</hi> imputation. And I thank you ſo much the more, as you were much more obliged (by Temptation) to defend your <hi>own,</hi> than I was to defend another mans.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. IV.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Conceſſions to the Doctors perſonal Worth, and Sence of his ill-treating the Doctors Name, thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledged.</head>
               <p>AS to what concerns your Intituling Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> to the twelve Arguments, according to your <hi>Printed</hi> Edition, and ſome ill reſented mixtures in your Contradictions of them; your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and ingenuous Expreſſions are ſuch, as well deſerve to be a <hi>Winding-ſheet</hi> to all Offences, which took life from your Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the Doctor. And firſt you ſay, that as to my Vindication of Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> Perſonal worth, you and I are agreed, and <hi>you have nothing in that to ſay againſt me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I thankfully acknowledge, and I ſhall not be the only Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſenſible of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſaid to confirm his <hi>own</hi> Statues, by ſecuring thoſe of <hi>Pompey.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106050:14"/>Beſide divers other Paſſages of the import aboveſaid, you have one in page 8. which I ſhall transfer <hi>hither</hi> for Reaſons I ſhall give by and by. <hi>I do but tell my Reaſons for naming the Doctor, but I undertake not to juſtifie either that, or the manner of my writings, from Miſtake, Imprudence, or other Faultineſs. I ſuppoſe you to be a man whom I take from my heart to be far better, and wiſer than my ſelf: And therefore as I thank you for your gentle, friendly Reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; ſo I profeſs that my very eſteem and Reverence of your Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment makes me ſuſpect that I have done amiſs; when I ſee it not in the cauſe it ſelf. That I could have difended the cauſe of Love, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion againſt thoſe Arguments; without taking notice of the Author, and without wronging the Nonconformiſts, who will be charged by his Name, I did, and do wiſh; Bue I thought it could not well be done: If in this I mistook, I ask pardon of God, and man; for ſo I must do for my Sins known and unknown.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More to this purpoſe the Reader may find in this page, and page 29. Thus far I have repeated your words, becauſe they are powerful Perſwaſions to <hi>Heart-Reconciliation,</hi> and allaying of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoſities; where Principles of Chriſtianity, or <hi>humanity</hi> prevail, and are attended to: And more likely to do good that way with <hi>moſt,</hi> than many ſtrong Reaſons of <hi>another</hi> Countenance, if they were to be had.</p>
               <p>And indeed Sir, you have in this Paſſage expreſſed ſo much of Humility, and Self-denyal; as few of <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſhall yet remain unſatisfied, would imitate under <hi>leſs</hi> difficult Circuniſtances. And I expect ſome may read them <hi>here,</hi> whoſe Prejudice will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to ſeek it <hi>elſewhere.</hi> The Value you are pleaſed to put upon the ſuppoſed Author, is (I confeſs) ſo great, that I ſhould not for <hi>Modeſty ſake</hi> have mentioned (much leſs <hi>aſſumed</hi>) but that (whoever you apprehend him to be) I have reaſon enough to transfer it upon ſome <hi>far more</hi> worthy Perſon then my ſelf.</p>
               <p>There is one thing pertaining to this head which I ſhall willingly diſpacth in this place; and it concerns a <hi>Requeſt</hi> of yours, an <hi>ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt</hi> Requeſt, <hi>Scil.</hi> pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 7. <hi>All that I yet deſire, is to be able to deny it to be his, that the next man that hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s the Nonconformiſts in the Teeth with it as the Doctors, may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> be told it is not his: If you can and will but tell me that you believe it not to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is, that I may have but ſo much to ſay; I will thank you, and make it publickly known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106050:15"/>Dear Sir, a far <hi>leſs</hi> earneſt Requeſt, yea leſs than a <hi>Requeſt,</hi> would have drawn from me a <hi>greater</hi> matter than this to gratifie you. <hi>I</hi> therefore ſay, that <hi>I</hi> cannot affirm, or deny it to be his, of mine <hi>own</hi> knowledge: for <hi>I</hi> never received it from his <hi>hand,</hi> nor ever heard him own or deny it to be his, more or leſs. As to what <hi>I</hi> believe of it, <hi>I</hi> ſhall be <hi>open,</hi> and ingenuous with you. <hi>I</hi> do believe that much of the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of it was written by the Doctor, and by him read to ſome few Perſons (probably to have their <hi>Opinion</hi> of it, and of what uſe it might be to ſome perſons concerned in the then <hi>preſent</hi> difficulties, (and not yet <hi>paſt</hi>) and that ſomebody having gotten the Copy, took Liberty to diſperſe it to ſome <hi>others,</hi> whoſe Caſe or Curioſity moved them to deſire it: But <hi>I</hi> do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that the Doctor intended it for the <hi>Preſs,</hi> or to be expoſed as it <hi>was,</hi> or that he ever <hi>wrote</hi> it, or owned it, or would have owned it <hi>his;</hi> as it is in <hi>your</hi> Edition, without very <hi>Conſiderable</hi> Alterations.</p>
               <p>And <hi>I</hi> having had ſince I wrote the Vindication, the <hi>like</hi> Opinion from ſome, who were <hi>moſt</hi> likely to know the <hi>whole</hi> truth of this matter: <hi>I</hi> am farther Confirmed in the belief of what <hi>I</hi> ſay now, and ſaid <hi>before</hi> in the Vindication, page 1. yet in my poor Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, 'tis enough for you that you cannot <hi>affirm</hi> it to be his: Nor any other who ſhall pretend it for <hi>whatever</hi> ends. And be it his, or <hi>not</hi> his, (ſeeing he did not think meet to avow it publickly) 'tis becoming wiſe men, to let it ſtand, or fall, according to its own <hi>proper</hi> merit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106050:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. V.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> fourth Section Conſidered, being a Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellaneous Collection of various matters Contained in the Vindicator, and his Animadverſions on them.</head>
               <p>THe Cloſe of the firſt Paragraph of your fourth Sect. page 29. gives a full <hi>Diſcharge</hi> to the Doctors Name, (ſo far as you concerned it in your Anſwer to the Manuſcript) in theſe words; <hi>I wholly follow the Rule you mention, to chuſe that which doth moſt good, and least hurt. And truly, the Reverence of your own, and ſome other Judgment telling me, that it doth more hurt than good, doth turn the Scales, and make me repent, that I named the Doctor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reverend Sir, I thank you for <hi>thus</hi> much, whoever or whatever was your Motive. And I ſhall the more patiently bear the load you diſcharge on <hi>me;</hi> though I ſhall take leave to <hi>poize</hi> it, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire <hi>Quo Warranto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A Warfare, a Voyage muſt not be <hi>undertaken,</hi> but with expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſome <hi>blowes,</hi> or <hi>foul</hi> Weather. After a <hi>Calm,</hi> comes a <hi>Storm,</hi> which was brewing all the while, I now perceive; and it begins thus, page 29. <hi>I leave your charges against me to their beſt Advantage to the Reader, though my Inclination as much to open Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes. I may give a brief touch to your ſelf, for your Information; which I expect not ſhould affect the Reader, ſuppoſe your book to lie open before you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is of rare example for <hi>any,</hi> much more Mr. <hi>Baxter, toto pectore, telum recipere;</hi> and not to expoſe miſtakes that are to his diſadvantage. But Sir, your brief touch for my Information, I expect it to be neither <hi>brief,</hi> nor a gentle touch, nor much to my information; except that in the beſt of men <hi>nature will work.</hi> And whereas you ſay, <hi>you expect not that it ſhould affect the Reader, &amp;c. I</hi> know not what to think of it, unleſs that your Readers have ſo littie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106050:16"/>cern for <hi>me,</hi> that if you ſhould clap a Cupping Glaſs to me, <hi>I</hi> ſhall have none of their pity. But <hi>I</hi> am not Doctor <hi>Owen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>You begin to inform me by <hi>examining</hi> me, and go on moſtly in that <hi>form</hi> of information; which ſeems to aim rather at your own: But to be brought to the Rack, and <hi>dicere cauſam</hi> is a hard Chapter ſaid <hi>A. B. Laud,</hi> If (ſay you) <hi>you thought them not good enough to be his, nor intended for publick view; Why do you wrong bim ſo much, and the people much more, as to divulge them with his name?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ſee Sir, you need to be better informed your <hi>ſelf</hi> of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, before you turn Informer to me. Who told you that <hi>I</hi> ever divulged them to any one perſon? And <hi>I</hi> tell you, that though <hi>I</hi> had ſeen them about a year <hi>before; I</hi> never <hi>read</hi> them, nor <hi>heard</hi> them read, except ſome <hi>part</hi> of them <hi>Curſorily once:</hi> And <hi>I</hi> never was Maſter of any one Copy of them, true or falſe; 'til <hi>I</hi> had your <hi>Printed</hi> Edition. <hi>I</hi> muſt therefore ſend this <hi>Quere</hi> home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to your <hi>ſelf,</hi> to whom it much more belongs than to <hi>me,</hi> and as the Divulger with his <hi>name,</hi> more <hi>I</hi> think than to all the world beſide.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>Do good men take it for a priviledge, to hurt the Church, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contradicted?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Why ask you me this queſtion, rather than of any other? You might have anſwered it your ſelf. Certainly none but the worſt of men take it for a priviledge under that name; but many <hi>good</hi> men <hi>do</hi> hurt the Church, and take it to be good (by miſtake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either the <hi>Church,</hi> or the <hi>hurt</hi>) Who theſe good men are is, <hi>lis ſub judice,</hi> all are ſaid by one or <hi>other</hi> to do it, all juſtifie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from it. Yet <hi>they</hi> may be moſt guilty of this <hi>ignorant zeal,</hi> (which is the beſt can be ſaid of it) that leaſt ſuſpect themſelves, and moſt hotly charge others: I will ſay for mine own part, that <hi>I</hi> need ſcarce any thing more to ſet my judgment right of my ſelf or others than <hi>impartial ſelf-reflection.</hi> By the queſtion you ſeem to ſay I am the man, and I will put it fairly to my ſelf. You may do as you pleaſe.</p>
               <p>You ſay, <hi>It is zeal for a Sect againſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, which corrupt nature is for.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And there is a zeal too for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which corrupt nature is for, and you are againſt. 'Tis too common a <hi>Cant</hi> to brand thoſe for <hi>Sects,</hi> that are not juſt of our own <hi>ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106050:16"/>A very eaſie and <hi>impertinent</hi> way of abuſing. A <hi>Cothurnus,</hi> that ſerves every ones turn.</p>
               <p>Again, <hi>I doubted not but guilt would be impatient. Anſw.</hi> What then? Is impatience a proof of <hi>guilt?</hi> or every defence againſt wrongs, impatience? You ſhould not have caſt <hi>this</hi> ſtone. You proceed:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was your Party that wronged his name, by divulging that which you take for his diſgrace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> My Party! Is not that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> for one? <hi>I</hi> found Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and the Doctors Vindicator of one Party in your Titles, <hi>without</hi> doors, and <hi>within;</hi> Who parted us ſince, and made me of another Party? Not <hi>I, I</hi> am ſure; <hi>I</hi> am the ſame <hi>I</hi> was; and that is, of no Party at all. But if you will diſagree with your <hi>ſelf,</hi> and make Parties in one ſingle individual, look you to that. Who of the Party do you mean who take the <hi>Manuſcript</hi> for the Doctors diſgrace? O! they were offended that it was printed under his name. And if you or any of your friends ſhould expreſs <hi>offence,</hi> at your Manuſcripts being Printed under <hi>your name,</hi> which you never intended for the Preſs, nor <hi>Conſented</hi> ſhould be ſo Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; would you allow <hi>this</hi> inference, that they were taken for your <hi>diſgrace?</hi> Beſide, whatever ſome may think of themſelves, I do not think, that the ableſt men ſpit ſuch perfections, as without Correction, or more ado, may without <hi>wrong</hi> to their names (and ſomewhat elſe too) be expoſed to the worſt that an adverſary can make of them.</p>
               <p>Page 30. you ſay, <hi>It's strange ſo knowing a man ſhould think that bad Arguments with avalued name, are not dangerous! Yes even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt common ſence, as thoſe for Tranſubſtantiation. To confute your ſelf, you add</hi> [Add to what?] <hi>that on all ſides peoples opinions are moſtly, and moſt STRONGLY mastered by Affections, and it's be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all our power to Cure the diſorder. And yet is there no danger from</hi> Names?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> You may croſs <hi>Shins,</hi> and fight againſt your ſelf when you <hi>pleaſe.</hi> I delight in no <hi>ſuch</hi> Combats: But its more ſtrange, that ſo <hi>pious</hi> a man ſhould take ſuch Courſes to wrong his very Friend, and render him Croſs to Truth, and himſelf at once, by a <hi>half-faced</hi> Repreſentation.</p>
               <p>Reader, all that the Reverend Author preteds to ground theſe two charge upon, is contained in a few Lines, of which by giving a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106050:17"/>he (I will not ſay cunningly) ſpoils, and perverts the ſence of the whole; they are in page 7. [<q>Dear Sir, I fear that thoſe People, who have not the skill to anſwer the twelve Arguments, will be found to want skill enough, to diſcover the <hi>Strength</hi> of <hi>yours.</hi> And I confeſs 'tis matter of <hi>Lamentation,</hi> that on all ſides Peoples Opinions are moſtly, and moſt ſtrongly maſter'd by their Affections; and 'tis beyond all our power to cure the Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.]</q>
               </p>
               <p>Now Reader, if acknowledging, and <hi>lamenting</hi> the danger alſo, be <hi>ſaying</hi> there is <hi>no</hi> danger in <hi>valued</hi> Names, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> is right, and <hi>I</hi> am not wronged.</p>
               <p>Truly Sir, I am ſorry that you cannot <hi>yet</hi> (after all you have ſaid) get over your naming the Doctor, but muſt be looking <hi>back</hi> to a Vindication of what you have ſo <hi>often,</hi> and ſo pathetically <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt,</hi> to be <hi>faulty.</hi> So hard a thing it is for good men, to digeſt a <hi>Self</hi> (but half <hi>Conſtrained</hi>) <hi>Condemnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I take leave to add, that the danger of deceiving by valued names, ſhould deeply oblige <hi>thoſe,</hi> whoſe names are <hi>much</hi> valued by one ſort or <hi>another,</hi> not to ſpeak or write <hi>hand over head,</hi> but with ſuch warineſs and Caution, that they may be <hi>indeed</hi> guides, and not <hi>Snares</hi> to their valuers. And to others, that they would have a care of <hi>over</hi>-valuing <hi>names,</hi> and learn to judge of things by their <hi>proper</hi> Evidence.</p>
               <p>Page 31. <hi>If numbring mens Errors, uſed to do hurt; be worſe than committing them, or defending them, I miſtook. I Conſent that you do ſo by me, ſo you ſpeak nothing but the Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> And did you not <hi>miſtake,</hi> if it was not <hi>worſe?</hi> I have thought hitherto, that to do <hi>ill</hi> was a <hi>miſtake</hi> (at leaſt) though not ſo bad, as that which is <hi>worſe.</hi> I thought alſo, that this was one manner of treating the Doctor, wherein you acknowledged your ſelf <hi>Faulty:</hi> But if you retract this, as you (ſeem alſo to) have done your <hi>other</hi> acknowledgments; <hi>I</hi> am at Liberty to recall my thanks. But for your Conſent that I ſhould give you the <hi>ſame</hi> meaſure, upon the Condition limiting, <hi>ſcil. of Truth:</hi> I ſhall not take you at your word; becauſe, I take <hi>Volenti non fit injuria,</hi> to be but a crooked Rule. Nor ſhall I (though with your <hi>leave</hi>) <hi>doubly</hi> condemn my ſelf, by doing that which I condemned in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:106050:17"/>In the ſame page you ſay, <hi>I am ſorry that you feign the healing Parliament to have diſowned our Repentance. They forbad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching and troubling one another; but not remembring our Sin, nor feeling when we ſuffer, nor asking what cauſed it; to ſtop the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, if not for a Cure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Sir, you teach here a Notion very new (at leaſt to me) <hi>ſcil.</hi> To affirm that which is not true in Argumentation, (which may be thro' miſtake) is to <hi>feign.</hi> Much joy Sir, of this <hi>invention,</hi> I wiſh you. But if you be never <hi>ſorry,</hi> 'till I feign or affirm that great <hi>Abſurdity, I</hi> hope that from henceforth you ſhall be a joyful man. If that Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the Act of Oblivion did not <hi>bar</hi> ſuch Criminations by <hi>any</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, much more by private Perſons. (whatever pretence they might make of cauſing the Criminals to <hi>repent</hi> of it, by ſo doing) <hi>I</hi> ſpake not <hi>their</hi> Sence, nor to <hi>my</hi> purpoſe: But if they <hi>did, I</hi> needed not (according to your notion) to <hi>feign,</hi> when <hi>I</hi> had ſuch <hi>Realities</hi> on my ſide.</p>
               <p>You ſay alſo in the ſame page, <hi>You would put ſuch terms upon me in diſpute, as</hi> Veron <hi>deviſed to put on the Proteſtants. I muſt oppoſe his Doctrine, only as in the Syllables written, Accidents in Worſhip ſignifie you think at leaſt an integral part.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I wiſh the Papiſts would never put <hi>harder</hi> Terms upon the Proteſtants, than not to <hi>corrupt</hi> their Arguments, by choping and changing Words at their <hi>Pleaſure;</hi> which you have often done in the Tract I examined: <hi>I</hi> told you of many ſuch faults; you deny not the Fact in <hi>one,</hi> but here you <hi>juſtifie</hi> it; and you juſtifie it <hi>here</hi> as an <hi>inſignificant</hi> Alteration. But you know that the Doctor thought not <hi>ſo,</hi> for he inſiſted on the ſence of that inſignificant Syllable, (as you take it) And <hi>I</hi> inſiſt on it in my Examination of your Anſwer, which the Reader may underſtand (if he will look into my Book) to be of another Countenance than your <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken</hi>-glaſs Repreſents. What work may men make with <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> if they take <hi>this</hi> Liberty, when they pretend to give the Authors own words; by all the Tokens uſual: if they ſhall chop and change Words, Syllables, or <hi>ſome</hi> one Letter! May they not put <hi>yea,</hi> in the room of <hi>nay;</hi> and <hi>nay</hi> in the room of <hi>yea;</hi> and make their Author ſpeak <hi>what,</hi> and no more then they liſt. 'Tis one thing to <hi>Commend</hi> exactneſs, and another to <hi>uſe</hi> it. But if you <hi>juſtifie</hi> this Liberty, we may expect you will take it for the future, and then there will be no dealing with you.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106050:18"/>Page 30. <hi>Its wiſely done not to own the Cauſe I oppoſe, and yet not let men know whether it be for fear of the Law, or becauſe you are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſuppoſe Sir you mean <hi>cunningly,</hi> a ſort of Wiſdom <hi>I</hi> am little acquainted with. <hi>I</hi> am too open and fair for <hi>ſuch</hi> Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. <hi>I</hi> told you the cauſe, <hi>page</hi> 3, <hi>page</hi> 23. and <hi>page</hi> 39. You might have given your ſelf ſufficient reaſons for it, without asking them of others, much more being told them. If you could not ſee them <hi>there,</hi> it may be to as little purpoſe to repeat them <hi>here.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> hope you do not think that <hi>Laws, Penal</hi> Laws, are not to be feared. What were they elſe made for? You have indeed writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten concerning the Dioceſan <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> Conſtitution, and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>impoſing,</hi> as a man that feared not the Laws. But you have made ſuch a Compenſation for <hi>that,</hi> by your Zeal expreſſed for the Lyturgy, and <hi>Lay</hi>-Conformity, as may plead your pardon for that wrong. <hi>I</hi> believe, and not <hi>I</hi> alone, that by your Writings, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and <hi>valued</hi> name, ſerving fleſh and blood with a Wind, (which is no friend to Loſſes and Croſſes) you have ſerved the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the <hi>preſent</hi> Conſtitution, beyond all that hath been ſaid for it by thoſe, whoſe <hi>Station</hi> may promiſe the ſervice of their <hi>ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt</hi> Abilities.</p>
               <p>But for <hi>the Cauſe you oppoſe,</hi> and oppoſe with ſo much <hi>heat,</hi> I have not found you always of the <hi>ſame</hi> mind. Change of Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath great influence on ſome (and not only the moſt <hi>infirm</hi>) Conſtitions. <hi>I</hi> beg your pardon if <hi>I</hi> make a little Retroſpect to your Sentiments by-paſt, and ſometime ſince.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> might begin with your <hi>Savoy</hi>-Diſpute or <hi>Conference,</hi> wherein 'tis offered againſt a Lyturgy, that <hi>Cold Prayers are like to have a cold Return.</hi> But that being <hi>viva voce,</hi> in tranſient breath, <hi>I</hi> ſhall not ſo much inſiſt on it; but remember you of what you ſaid elſewhere, for Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But we think it was not the Jeſuites that firſt ſaid,</hi> Out of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the Heart, the Mouth ſpeaketh. <hi>'Tis natural for the</hi> Heart <hi>to lead the</hi> Tongue. <hi>And men are more affected by words which come from</hi> Affection, <hi>than by thoſe that do not. And reading words written by</hi> another, <hi>when we ſpeak to God, is not ſo natural a Signification of Deſire, or other Affection; as ſpeaking them from the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106050:18"/>preſent Dictate of the Heart; for any Child can do the</hi> one, <hi>and it is not the uſual Signification of</hi> Seriouſneſs <hi>in other Actions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Miniſters ſhould be better acquainted than the People, how to ſpeak to God and man. It is their Office, and therefore, it belongeth to them to chuſe the</hi> Words, <hi>which are fittest: and to ſet up a Miniſtry that can do</hi> neither, <hi>is to befriend the Prince of</hi> Darkneſs <hi>againſt the Kingdom of Light, and to be a</hi> deadly <hi>Enemy to the Church and Souls; and to ſit up a Miniſtry that</hi> need <hi>not do it, is the way to ſet up a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry that</hi> cannot. <hi>Let the Miniſters be</hi> bound <hi>to no more than to read, and a</hi> few <hi>years will transform them to</hi> ſuch <hi>as can do</hi> no more <hi>than read. Baxters</hi> ſecond Defence of the meer Nonconformiſts, <hi>page</hi> 15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I doubt not, but there are</hi> ſome <hi>pious Perſons among</hi> you, <hi>I Cenſure not farther than</hi> Experience <hi>conſtraineth me. But I know that the Common Sence of</hi> moſt <hi>that are</hi> ſerious <hi>in practical Chriſtianity, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your</hi> formal <hi>wayes of</hi> Worſhip; <hi>and againſt the Courſe that you have taken in this Land. And the Spirit of</hi> Prophaneſs <hi>Comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth with you, and</hi> doteth <hi>on you,</hi> in all <hi>places that ever I was acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in. Bear with</hi> plain <hi>Truth: It is in a Cauſe of</hi> Everlaſting <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. There is</hi> ſomewhat <hi>in a graciou Soul, like</hi> Health <hi>in the Body, that diſpoſeth it to</hi> Reliſh wholſom <hi>food, and perceive</hi> more <hi>difference between it, and</hi> meer Air, <hi>or toyiſh Kick-ſhaws, than it can</hi> eaſily expreſs. Baxters <hi>fifth Diſpute of Church-Government Pref. page</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Compare this with Mr. <hi>Baxters</hi> Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Owens</hi> twelve Arguments, Page 42.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And if it be the</hi> diſuſe <hi>of your</hi> Common-prayer, <hi>that you ſeparate from us for, I would know of you, Whether you would have</hi> denyed <hi>Communion with</hi> all <hi>that lived before it had a</hi> Being? <hi>If this be your</hi> Religion, <hi>I may ask you,</hi> Where <hi>was your</hi> Religion <hi>before Luther, before King</hi> Edwards <hi>day? If you ſay in the</hi> Maſs-book, (And what elſe can you ſay) <hi>I ask you then, where was it before the</hi> Maſs-book <hi>had a Being?</hi> Baxters <hi>fifth Diſpute, &amp;c. Pref. page</hi> 30.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Could men have been content to have made Gods Laws the</hi> Centre, <hi>and Touch-ſtone of the Churches</hi> Unity, <hi>all had been well. But when they muſt make</hi> Cannons <hi>for this</hi> Veſture, <hi>and that</hi> Geſture, <hi>and the other</hi> Ceremony; <hi>and determine in what</hi> Words <hi>all men ſhall pray,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106050:19"/>and how</hi> many <hi>words he ſhall ſay, or how long he ſhall be; and ſo make</hi> ſtanding <hi>Laws upon</hi> mutable <hi>Circumstances; and this without any Neceſſity</hi> at all, <hi>but only to</hi> Domineer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Baxters <hi>fifth Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, page</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They [the Phariſees] uſed</hi> long <hi>Prayers, as a Cloak for their Oppreſſion. Query, Whether they were a</hi> Lyturgy or not? <hi>If</hi> yea, <hi>ſo let it paſs in</hi> their <hi>Character. If</hi> not, <hi>Then it is ſcarce like that there was any</hi> other <hi>Lyturgy than the</hi> Scripture <hi>in</hi> thoſe <hi>times; elſe it is</hi> moſt <hi>likely that the</hi> Phariſees <hi>would have</hi> uſed it. Apology for Nonconformiſts, <hi>page</hi> 95.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to ſet up</hi> a new ſort <hi>of Juriſdiction in the Church, by Legiſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to make</hi> Forms and Ceremonies <hi>Obligatory; and by Executions to puniſh Paſtors that will not practice them is,</hi>—</p>
               <p>Laſtly, <hi>By this means you will</hi> harden the Papiſts, <hi>that by their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions and impoſitions have</hi> divided <hi>the Church, and been guilty of ſo much impoſition and Tyranny. For, how can we condemn that in</hi> them <hi>that is practiced by our</hi> ſelves? <hi>And though in</hi> number <hi>of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions they</hi> exceed; <hi>yet it is not well to concur with them in the</hi> kind <hi>of unneceſſary Impoſitions, and ſo far to</hi> juſtifie <hi>them in their injury to the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If none of theſe or</hi> other <hi>reaſons, will allay the</hi> imperious <hi>Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the proud; but they muſt needs</hi> (<hi>by an</hi> uſurped Legiſlation) <hi>be making</hi> indifferent <hi>things become</hi> neceſſary <hi>to others, and domineer over mens Conſciences, and the Church of God: We must leave them to him, that being Lord and</hi> Lawgiver <hi>of the Church, is jealous of</hi> His <hi>Prerogative, and abhorreth IDOLS, and will not give</hi> His <hi>Glory to</hi> another, <hi>and that delighteth to pull down the proud, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them that Exalt themſelves.</hi> Baxters <hi>5th Diſpute of Church-Government, page</hi> 378.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That to that very Queſtion [Whether they know of any thing in the Lyturgy, with which they could not comply without Sin] we after gave in a Paper of</hi> eight <hi>particulars in the Lyturgy, which we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took to prove</hi> flat ſin. Apology for meer Nonconformiſts, <hi>page</hi> 155.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moreover, the</hi> ſame <hi>reaſons that prevail with</hi> us, <hi>will prevail with</hi> others <hi>when we are</hi> dead. <hi>They will be as</hi> fearful <hi>of Lying, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, and of ſwearing Allegiance to Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpers, as we have been. There will ſtill be a People</hi> ſeriouſly Religious, <hi>that are Chriſtians in</hi> good ſadneſs, <hi>and</hi> really <hi>believe a Life to</hi> come. <hi>There is no hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it; God will have it</hi> ſo, <hi>and who can gainſay</hi> Him? <hi>And theſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106050:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>men will be as loath in point of</hi> Order and Decency, <hi>to have Religion dwindled into</hi> a lifeleſs form of Words and Ceremonies; <hi>and to take the Chaff and ſtraw for the Corn; as ever</hi> we <hi>have been before them: And the Hiſtory of</hi> our Sufferings, <hi>will but</hi> animate them, <hi>id. ibidem, page</hi> 19<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Theſe are not <hi>all</hi> I have to alledge of <hi>yours,</hi> of the ſame <hi>Colour.</hi> Whether you will count your Writings of <hi>this Nature,</hi> or thoſe which <hi>contradict</hi> them for your <hi>Diſgrace, I</hi> cannot tell. I am ſure both <hi>cannot</hi> (if conſidered together) much raiſe the value of <hi>your Authority</hi> in this Controverſy. And I think, if <hi>I</hi> had been minded to have vindicated all the twelve Arguments you brand as <hi>ſo faulty, I</hi> could have produced, to juſtifie moſt of what you ſay is moſt unjuſtifiable, not only by your <hi>Authority,</hi> but your <hi>Reaſons</hi> alſo, made ready to my <hi>hand:</hi> but that was not my undertaking in that Tract. If any doubt of my fidelity in theſe Citations, <hi>I</hi> give them the books, and pages, wherein they may find them to a Word. My Credit is impaired, if not forfeited, by a wilful or negligent Failure. But if it ſhould be demanded, how Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> Judgment and <hi>Zeal</hi> could thus <hi>vary and oppoſe</hi> to ſuch a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree? I can give them no farther light than this. That theſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Paſſages were Printed in the years 1659, 61, or 62, &amp; 81. But that againſt the twelve Arguments in 84.</p>
               <p>I am heartily averſe to writing any thing in reply to you, that ſavours of wrangling; eſpecially in Perſonal Concerns: But if you will neceſſitate me by ſuch <hi>Reflecting</hi> Queries, to anſwer ſo as is unpleaſing to us <hi>both; I</hi> cannot help that. There is one behind, which I muſt not <hi>omit,</hi> which contains a Charge that (if <hi>true</hi>) renders me ſo great a fool, and ſo foul an Offender, as to be <hi>utterly</hi> unfit to be concerned in any thing that requires either Judgment, or <hi>Common</hi> Honeſty: But if it be <hi>falſe</hi> (as indeed it is) I leave you, and the Reader to make the right Conſtruction.</p>
               <p>You ſay, Page 30. <hi>If the work</hi> [the Manuſcript] <hi>be faulty, why do you not joyn with me to ſave men from it? and why did your private Letter own it his Conjunct with Fame? I offered you to ſtop it. Is it diſingenuity in me, to tell you of twenty untruths in your Letter; and many notorious:</hi> [you ſay in your <hi>Printed</hi> anſwer to the <hi>unknown</hi> Author, they are Untruths in matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> which aggravates their Faultineſs] <hi>and ingenuity in you to be offended for being told of them, rather than for writing them? This is to comply with the World
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106050:20"/>that taketh the Detecter for the only Sinner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the firſt <hi>I</hi> ſay, <hi>fair and ſoftly.</hi> Let your <hi>own</hi> Act. In oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Manuſcript be firſt excuſed, or <hi>excuſable</hi> (at leaſt in my Opinion) before I am perſwaded to joyn with you in it. <hi>I</hi> may add, what needed this, if you believed the <hi>Title</hi> you give to the Book <hi>I</hi> now anſwer? or had not <hi>forgot</hi> it before you writ Page 30?</p>
               <p>To the ſecond, you lay to my charge things that <hi>I</hi> know not. You ſay it <hi>to</hi> and <hi>of</hi> the Author of the Vindication. In your Poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of your Anſwer to the 12 Arguments, he was to you the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known</hi> Author, but in your Anſwer to my Vindication, you are ſo well, or ſo <hi>ill</hi> informed of the Author of that ſo <hi>faulty</hi> Letter, that without any doubting you fix it on <hi>me.</hi> I gave you no reaſon for it; nor could any other. And that Opinion you expreſs frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Author of the Vindication, doth not well agree with the great imprudence you charge on the private Letter. But in ſhort Sir, I affirm (who have the beſt means to know it) that I wrote not that, nor any other Letter to you theſe many years laſt paſt; neither had I any knowledge of the Agitations you ſpeak of. And ſhould I have ſaid in a Letter to you, that the Manuſcript was the Doctors, &amp; afterward in Print ſaid I did not believe it, (as you print it) &amp; have blamed you for imputing it to him; I had played a very diſingenuous and inexcuſable part; Trepan'd you into a Miſtake, and then expoſed it. But as the Caſe ſtands, I ſhall only ſay, that your charging me therewith was but an <hi>inexcuſable Slander,</hi> or the indifferent thing (ſuppoſing the Letter as bad as you repreſent it) of laying the Puniſhment of one mans guilt, on the next that ſtood in your Way. Yet Sir, I believe this was no <hi>wilful</hi> wrong done by you, but a Miſtake for want of <hi>due</hi> Conſideration. But this it is to be a <hi>Nameleſs</hi> Author; inſtead of <hi>no</hi> Name, to get a <hi>bad</hi> one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:106050:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>SECT. VI.</hi> Of Repentance in Heaven, and the Diſpleaſure of Glory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Saints there, at their Miſtakes defended on Earth, aſſerted by Mr. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SOmewhat, Reverend Sir, I muſt ſay to your third Section, <hi>page</hi> 15. but as little as the thing will bear, it being but <hi>accidental</hi> to the preſent buſineſs, though you ſpend eleven pages upon in. I had aſſerted, that if Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> were undoubtedly diſpleaſed at his <hi>miſtakes,</hi> being defended by <hi>any one</hi> on Earth, <hi>now</hi> he in a glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Soul in Heaven, he muſt <hi>undoubtedly</hi> have the knowledge of ſuch a Defence. And that affirming ſuch a knowledge, would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive us of our <hi>best</hi> Weapon againſt the Idolatry and Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Papiſts, in their invocation of Saints.</p>
               <p>In Anſwer to this page, 16. (beſide ſome ſportive Paſſages) you extend the Knowledge of the I Saints in Heaven, an far as <hi>remi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcence,</hi> and rational Concluſions from what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſupplies them with will go. And I think Sir, you have therein ſaid, all that can be ſaid with <hi>Reaſon,</hi> (as for what God in mediately, or by Angels may reveal to them, is no ground to us; unleſs we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it better) but ſeeing you go no farther than ſtrong <hi>Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities,</hi> as to the preſent inſtance: your <hi>undoubtedly</hi> is not without doubt, and I am ſafe enough yet.</p>
               <p>But Sir, I think you venture too hard, to argue from thoſe <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks</hi> of the Saints judging the World, and the Extention of a Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beam. The firſt may be done Congruouſly <hi>enough,</hi> by their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying Chriſt in that Action, and applauding his Juſtice in its <hi>Execution;</hi> which they may know to be <hi>ſuch,</hi> by the ability and intogrity of ſuch a Judge; beſide the Book of Evidence, that ſhall then be opened.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:106050:21"/>But if this be any thing to <hi>your</hi> purpoſe, you muſt ſuppoſe them to know <hi>all</hi> that is done in the World in all the <hi>parts</hi> of it. Now to make this <hi>feaſible,</hi> your other <hi>Notion</hi> falls in as pat as can be. <hi>Nor that they live as unconcerned Strangers to Earth, when a Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beam can reach ſo far, page</hi> 16. You ſeem here to <hi>fancy</hi> that the Souls in Heaven ought <hi>rationally</hi> to be concluded, to have a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>terrene</hi> things, as <hi>extenſive,</hi> and penetrating as the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beams at <hi>leaſt.</hi> But yet conſidering, that the denſe Body of the Earth doth ſo interpoſe, that it muſt be beholding to its <hi>Circular</hi> motion, to viſit with its <hi>direct</hi> beams all the inhabitants of this earthly Globe; that will not ſerve <hi>your</hi> turn, unleſs you fancy alſo their ſtation and motion equally (at leaſt) Coreſpondent. But by this, and what follows, you ſeem your ſelf a little affected with the <hi>Vertigo.</hi> For, you provide <hi>theſe,</hi> with other Antidotes, <hi>leaſt I faign them to have News-books, Gazets, and Poſt-letters hence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Sir, this Caution belongs rather to thoſe, who will needs have them ſo exactly <hi>knowing</hi> of our Concerns here below; and you ſeem to be in ſome danger of in, ſince you have already begun the <hi>Correſpondence,</hi> by a thing in the form of an Epiſtle from Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in Heaven, in your Poſtſcript to your Anſwer to the twelve Arguments.</p>
               <p>Of much the ſame <hi>humour,</hi> is your ſorrow and deſperation of my change of my Opinion of the <hi>uncertainty</hi> of the Saints know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what, and when we pray; [for ſo I expreſſed my Opinion] to be my <hi>beſt Weapon againſt the Popiſh Superſtition of praying to Saints.</hi> Yet for all <hi>this,</hi> you will hope, that I do not pray to Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> for ſo much as I believe he <hi>knoweth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, nor to Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> neither, if he were in Heavon, and as knowing as <hi>he.</hi> For, though I ſhall ſtill retain this Weapon as our <hi>beſt,</hi> we have ſtore of others good enough againſt <hi>that</hi> Foppery. I preſume you will hold me excuſed for anſwering you in <hi>your</hi> kind: <hi>Hanc veniam — petimuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> viciſſim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That the Saints in Heaven have <hi>diſpleaſure,</hi> which you affirm in Contradiction to me; <hi>I</hi> am now to conſider. You begin very <hi>warily,</hi> page 16. and confine it to <hi>Diſplicence,</hi> the contrary to that <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence</hi> which is in the <hi>will:</hi> ſaying, <hi>As pleaſedneſs and diſ-pleaſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs are in the Paſſions, and ſignifie joy and</hi> trouble, <hi>you have here no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with them (having expreſly excluded ſorrow) but in the Will.</hi> So that it ſeems we are agreed that there is no diſpleaſure
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106050:21"/>as in the <hi>Paſſions,</hi> which is the ſame ſence with the vulgar Word <hi>Affections.</hi> But here you firſt ſuppoſe that I muſt not imagine you ſhould <hi>Contradict</hi> your ſelf. For this, I crave you pardon! 'tis <hi>more</hi> than poſſible.</p>
               <p>To make <hi>ſure</hi> work, you fetch your arm <hi>about</hi> and will prove that in God himſelf there is diſpleaſure, (which is the word you muſt allow, or you contradict not me) and then the <hi>Conſequence</hi> is undeniable, that gloryfied Souls are not leſs, but more capable of it. While you bring Scripture to prove this, who <hi>dare</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict it? and in this you are not ſparing; for you fill up your nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth page with Scripture Quotations, to <hi>Convince</hi> me that the Scripture ſaith God is <hi>diſpleaſed.</hi> A Child in his Pſalter knows this; your <hi>Concordance</hi> would (without much pains-taking) have furniſhed you with five times as many.</p>
               <p>But what earnings do you make of all theſe <hi>Scripture</hi> Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Do any of them ſay that this diſpleaſure is <hi>Confin'd</hi> to his <hi>Will,</hi> and hath nothing to do with <hi>ſorrow,</hi> the Affections or Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Doth not the Scripture ſay, that God was <hi>grieved,</hi> pained at the very <hi>Heart,</hi> angry, yea, in <hi>fury?</hi> do not theſe expreſs <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure</hi> or diſplicence, as in the <hi>Paſſions;</hi> contrary to joy and <hi>Peace?</hi> The Scripture alſo ſpeaks of Gods Eyes, Arm, Hand; you cannot make <hi>theſe flouriſhes</hi> of Scripture, but only to make a ſhew to the moſt ignorant: You know Sir, that 'tis not to be taken <hi>in proprio ſenſu.</hi> God ſpeaks to <hi>men,</hi> therefore ſpeaks after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men; make your inference now, and what will you get by it. God ſpeaks of himſelf to <hi>men</hi> after the manner of <hi>men; Ergo</hi> we may ſpeak of men after the manner of <hi>God.</hi> To as much <hi>pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,</hi> you tell us of all the forreign <hi>Reformers,</hi> and of <hi>Hilderſham, Dod, Greenham, Bolton, Rogers, Sibbs, Preston, page</hi> 20. All theſe ſaid God was diſpleaſed in the Scripture Sence; not one of them (that you prove) ſaid it in your ſence: nor can you (I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) produce one of them, that ever ſaid that the Saints are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to theſe Expreſſions of Gods <hi>Diſpleaſure, Grief, Anger, &amp;c.</hi> they relate to the Acts of Gods Providence, which are <hi>ad extra,</hi> which in men are the Signs and Effects of ſuch Affections or Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: But it follows not, that they are indications of the ſame things in God; which if they are in him, muſt be infinitely and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially ſo.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:106050:22"/>As for School mens Diſputes, and the Notions of Metaphyſical Authors of this matter, if I were better acquainted with them than I am, I ſhould not here concern my ſelf much with them, who too often do <hi>inſanire cum ratione</hi> about little things, much more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout God whoſe Perfections are ſo above humane Comprehenſion. But to reduce this diſpute to a narrow Compaſs; <hi>I</hi> agree with you, that as in the Divine Underſtanding all Sin is evil, and diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved or diſliked; ſo there is in the <hi>Will</hi> of God ſomewhat an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to it; But by what <hi>Name</hi> to call it, I am not reſolved by all the Conduct I have yet met with. Nor am <hi>I</hi> ſatisfied to call it <hi>milling,</hi> which you make <hi>univocal</hi> (or near it) with <hi>Diſplicerve</hi> as many of the School-men do; becauſe it ſounds too <hi>harſhly,</hi> as if that might <hi>be,</hi> the <hi>being</hi> of which God doth <hi>will;</hi> and ſo Gods <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition</hi> or Will by Conſequence be <hi>Croſſed</hi> or Contradicted. And if you Conſtrue your <hi>diſpleaſed</hi> by diſplicence, and that by <hi>Nolition,</hi> (except as Nolition may be in the Underſtanding) I can ſee no reaſon (pardon my dulneſs) to receive it.</p>
               <p>And whereas you ſay, page 19. <hi>The. Hebrew Phraſe which we tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate by diſpleaſing to God or man, is oft</hi> [it was Evil in his Eyes.] <hi>which ſpeakoth a Poſitive Act of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> de malo: <hi>And that there was no anſwerable Act of the Will, let him ſay that dares: I</hi> am not <hi>ſo daring</hi> as to ſay by what name it muſt, or may be called; yet ſeeing I have ſaid in the Book, and place you <hi>here</hi> oppoſe, tho' in Heaven there is <hi>diſlike</hi> and diſ-approbation; (which you your <hi>ſelf</hi> agree to be much of your ſence of diſpleaſure) you might have abated very many of your Reflections. And <hi>I now ſay,</hi> that God <hi>willing</hi> the Puniſhments of Sin, is an Act of his <hi>Will;</hi> and the Puniſhments Executed the <hi>Effects</hi> of that <hi>willing,</hi> or Act of his Will. And <hi>I</hi> hope you will not <hi>deny,</hi> but this is very anſwerable to the Act of Gods Underſtanding <hi>de malo;</hi> and <hi>I</hi> may be excuſed ſaying more as to the Act of Gods will <hi>de malo.</hi> Thus far we ſhall not much fall out.</p>
               <p>All your diſcourſe here of diſpleaſure in God, hath been to make way for this <hi>Conſequence,</hi> that a gloriſied Soul in Heaven may be <hi>diſpleaſed,</hi> exempli gratia, Dr. <hi>Owen</hi>'s. But what if it <hi>appear,</hi> that you have <hi>miſtaken,</hi> yea expreſly <hi>excluded</hi> the Queſtion (you ought to have put) hither to? And you your ſelf miſtook in your <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion,</hi> and not <hi>I</hi> in my Expoſition? <hi>I</hi> think this will appear by your <hi>Comparative.</hi> You ſay, <hi>I doubt not but by defending it,</hi> [the Doctors Miſtake] <hi>you far more diſpleaſe him than me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:106050:22"/>Here is <hi>only</hi> term without <hi>Explication,</hi> by which the Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of an evil by Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> in <hi>Meaven,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> on <hi>Earth,</hi> is expreſſed; and that is <hi>[diſpleaſed]</hi> and all the difference of this diſpleaſedneſs <hi>eexpreſſed,</hi> is but <hi>Secundum magis &amp; minus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Owen</hi> more diſpleaſed than Mr. <hi>Baxter;</hi> but the diſpleaſure is of the ſame <hi>identical Species,</hi> (excepting ſorrow) but if ſorrow be <hi>excepted,</hi> all the reſt that is included in the Diſpleaſure is <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; Exceptio firmat do non exceptis.</hi> And that includes (as it is or may be in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> at the ſaid <hi>miſtake</hi>) Anger, Wrath, Bitterneſs, Perturbation; and if you can excuſe your ſelf totally of <hi>Sinful Hatred</hi> of the Perſons that diſpleaſe you, it is more than many a very good man can do in the like Caſe. None of theſe are excepted by excluding <hi>Sorrow:</hi> yea ſuch is the <hi>Vitiouſneſs</hi> of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Nature, that the beſt of men do (while prevailed on by theſe Paſſions) take too much pleaſure in them. <hi>I</hi> hope now you will not ſay, that the Saints in Heaven may be affected with ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure.</p>
               <p>If you will needs ſpeak Myſteries, in a caſe where no ſuch things are neceſſary, or to the Purpoſe; and limit your ſence of your Expreſſions no <hi>better,</hi> you may excuſe your Readers miſtaking you, while they conſtrue your meaning by your <hi>words,</hi> which you ſeem to frame with exact <hi>Conſideration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now Sir, give me leave to look back on that <hi>very harſh</hi> Concluſion, you make by all the links (good or bad) of the Chain of your Conſequences, from my ſaying, that the Saints have <hi>no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure</hi> in Heaven, in Contradiction to Mr. <hi>Baxter:</hi> for that is all that is <hi>mine,</hi> the reſt is your own, and you muſt anſwer for them. <hi>I look</hi> (ſay you, page 22.) <hi>to hear ere long, from Preſs and Pulpits, that the Nonconformiſts teach, that no Rebellion, Treaſon, Perjury, or Wickedneſs, is at all diſpleaſing to God, to Chriſt, to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, or to any Saint in Heaven. Though they call Adulterers, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, and ſuch others to Repentance, and mouring for Sin; and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from others as too bad for their Communion. Indeed at the ſame time, they tell all the Wicked, neither God, nor any in Heaven is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do you indeed look for this! <hi>I</hi> am verily perſwaded not any of the moſt angry Adverſaries of the Nonconformiſts, with all their Wit, would from that Paſſage have <hi>thought</hi> of ſuch a <hi>horrible</hi> Charge, as having the leaſt ſhadow of <hi>rational</hi> dependance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106050:23"/>But now you have <hi>taught</hi> it them, and they have Mr. <hi>Baxters.</hi> Authority to do that, which <hi>I</hi> believe they will be aſhamed to do notwithſtanding. O Sir, to what Extremities, and beyond Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities do you run things! I believe in this fit of <hi>Diſpleaſure</hi> you had little <hi>Sorrow.</hi> What will become of the <hi>Saints Reſt,</hi> if ſuch Diſpleaſure be found amongſt the Saints in Heaven? Doth this ſpeak you to be a meet man to Reconcile, make peace, and heal the Churches Wounds; who know not how to <hi>breathe</hi> in a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy,</hi> but it muſt come to a <hi>Hurricane?</hi> The Lord be merciful to his Church, &amp; every part of it, &amp; deliver them from ſuch Products of impatience of Contradiction, &amp; from ſo <hi>over-valuing</hi> any Perſon, as to dote on his Conduct, without <hi>trying,</hi> and eſpecially Conſidering what <hi>Spirit</hi> he is of.</p>
               <p>You ſeem to heal <hi>all again</hi> in the next Paragraph, by mollifying my Error (as you call it) as meerly <hi>Verbal.</hi> Thus you blaſt, overthrow, wound, arm Adverſaries with venemous Weapons; add to the griefs of the already afflicted; and then cure all in a Trice, with a breath: as if theſe things were at your beck, and muſt move exactly to the Tune of your preſent fancies or <hi>Paſſions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall now conſider, what you ſay of <hi>Repentance</hi> in Heaven. You begin thus: <hi>My third ſuppoſed Error is much like the former; ſaying, that though Heaven have no Sorrow, it hath great Repentance: In this all Proteſtants are falſly ſaid to be againſt me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> You have in theſe words a <hi>double Miſtake</hi> in matter of <hi>Fact.</hi> I neither ſaid it was an <hi>Error,</hi> nor that I ſuppoſed it to be an Error. (though it may be ſuch notwithſtanding) Nor did I ſay, that <hi>in this</hi> all Proteſtants are againſt you. So that what you make the ground of this part of the Controverſy, is <hi>all</hi> Miſtake. Yet you go on, and tell your Reader that I am puzled at it as a <hi>dangerous</hi> Doctrine: though your <hi>next</hi> line <hi>acknowledges,</hi> that I attempt not in one Syllable to blame any thing but the <hi>Word.</hi> And had I not reaſon for ſo doing, and to ſay as I did, that it doth and will ſound very <hi>offenſively;</hi> &amp; moſt by far, will either not underſtand you, or <hi>miſunderſtand</hi> you? Do you think that School Subtilties, and thoſe Reconciling Notions which you are ſo ſtored with, are the Talents of moſt that may happen to read your Book? And that they can tell what to make of Repentance in Heaven &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>Sorrow?</hi> you have ſaid ſomewhat to inform or <hi>exerciſe</hi> their intellects in this, but not one Word in <hi>that</hi> Book.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:106050:23"/>And now Sir, I take my ſelf to be as little obliged to Anſwer, or Conſider what you ſay farther, (as <hi>Contradicting</hi> any thing ſaid by me) as you had to write it; and that is none at all. But becauſe (much like the former) you contrive from theſe miſtakes of your <hi>own,</hi> a very black (I had almoſt ſaid a <hi>Malevolent</hi>) Concluſion; I ſhall obſerve now you ſetch it about. Your Concluſion is this, page 25. <hi>I doubt not but thoſe aforeſaid,</hi> [Vide page 22.] <hi>that are diſpoſed to Obloquy, will take occaſion from your Words, (yea the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts from your intituling all Proteſtants to it) to ſay the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts (or the Proteſtants) hold that Murder, Rebellion, Perſecution, and all Sin is ſo ſmall a matter to their Saints in Heaven, that they do not ſo much as repent of it, or will, or wiſh they had never done it: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, they either juſtifie it, or are Neuters to it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Do you think the men you ſpeak of have ſuch a high Opinion of your Logical <hi>Concluding</hi> Faculty, as to charge men with holding all that you <hi>ſay</hi> are the <hi>Conſequences</hi> of their Opinion? They are wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than <hi>ſo</hi> for their <hi>own</hi> ſakes. Or may they not as well conclude much of the like nature, from our (or your) Saints in Heaven, not being <hi>ſorry</hi> for any of theſe Crimes? You ſaid you lookt for ſuch Reflections, page 22. here you <hi>doubt not</hi> of them. But pardon me if I ſay, that I expect the men you ſpeak of are maſters of ſo much Reaſon, Truth and Candor, that they will rather ſay, That in theſe Concluſions, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> conſulted not the Premiſes nor himſelf.</p>
               <p>Now Sir, I ſhall Conſider how you came by your <hi>diſmal</hi> Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, (ſuppoſing I had charged you with <hi>Error</hi> in that Expreſſion; and had alſo ſaid, that herein all Proteſtants are againſt you; both which you ſaid of me untruly) And I fear, that your hammering to mend <hi>one</hi> hole, hath made more than <hi>two;</hi> the uſual iſſue of <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, you tell me of <hi>Gods</hi> being ſaid to <hi>repent</hi> in Scripture. Now leaſt I ſhould not <hi>believe</hi> it, or take one Scripture Authority for no <hi>ſufficient</hi> Conviction; you direct me by Quotations to <hi>fifteen.</hi> I thank you for this great Charity and <hi>neceſſary</hi> pains. But what is all this to the Purpoſe? Dare you ſay that <hi>proprie dictum</hi> God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents, or deny that ſpoken of him it is a denomination from the Changes he makes <hi>ad extra;</hi> as the Effects of his eternal and <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable</hi> Will, without any change in himſelf? You tell me at next word, that <hi>'tis not ſpoken of God, as if he had any Mutability as man hath.</hi> And yet you add, as mighty unwilling to acknowledge your Scripture inſtances <hi>impertinent</hi> here: <hi>But God being infinitely</hi> more
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106050:24"/>
                  <hi>perfect, the Phraſe is farther fetched, and</hi> leſs <hi>proper of God than of</hi> man: <hi>Therefore it is not the name that he blameth, ſeeing he owneth the word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Reverend Sir, I obſerve you go here <hi>all</hi> by Comparatives: <hi>Muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> as <hi>man hath; infinitely</hi> more <hi>perfect than man, further fetch'd:</hi> All which I ſhould have taken no notice of; but becauſe of the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words, that the phraſe of God repenting, is <hi>leſs proper of God than of Man.</hi> This plainly renders it your opinion, that Repentance is <hi>proper</hi> to God (as contradiſtinguiſht from figurative) though in a leſs degree, and <hi>farther fetcht,</hi> than when ſpoken of man: which opinion whether it be not <hi>utterly</hi> untrue, and unſpeakably dangerous, I refer to the Judicious Reader. I would you had told us how much leſs proper, and how much <hi>farther fetcht,</hi> when ſpoken of God. To what you conclude, <hi>It is not therefore the name, &amp;c.</hi> I ſay I blame not the word repentance 'tis true; but your (at leaſt) indiſcreet, if not impertinent uſe and miſapplication of it.</p>
               <p>You acknowledg, that <hi>I</hi> had prevented your labour in tranſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing other Authors, that uſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> uſually for a meer change of the mind, purpoſe and practice, without any ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſorrow. And <hi>I</hi> alſo told you, that if you had ſaid the Saints in heaven were grown wiſer, had a better underſtanding, and did diſapprove of what they in this life thought good and true; This might (if nothing elſe) have ſtopped your torrent of diſmal conſequences, for they who do ſo, are far from juſtifying or being Neuters as (you expreſs it) as to Murder, Rebellion, Perſecution and all ſin as a ſmall matter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet you ſay page 23. <hi>But let us willingly take the Scripture uſe, which ſpeaketh of Repentance in heaven, and on Earth. Anſw.</hi> We have nothing to do in this Controverſy, with repentance of any on earth: but of the Saints in heaven. And you tell us at the bottom of the ſame page, that <hi>we find no talk in Scripture of any in heaven repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but God.</hi> Can I wiſh a fairer adverſary? That ſhall more wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly and expreſly yield the Cauſe? But by the next Paragraph you <hi>repent</hi> all this again, and ſay; <hi>All thoſe acts of Repentance Souls have in heaven:</hi> which riſe to the number of five. So that you can talk of what Souls do in Heaven, that by your own <hi>confeſſion</hi> within five lines before, the Scripture is utterly ſilent in. Have you any Revelation peculiar to your ſelf of thoſe things?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> muſt alſo Reverend Sir, enter my diſſent to ſome other paſſages upon the ſubject of Repentance in this life, to which you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106050:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>to direct me page 24. in that you ſay, <hi>But uſually we have cauſe of ſorrow, as well as of Repentance; and muſt joyn them together: But where the Goſpel frequently promiſeth Repentance, Pardon and Life to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and Preacheth both Repenting and Believing in order to preſent joy; there is little mention of ſorrow in the Converts, ſave for the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of Chriſt, or ſome great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Anſw.</hi> Is this a ſafe <hi>limitation</hi> to ſay <hi>uſually,</hi> which excludes ſorrow from our Repentance even in this life very <hi>often,</hi> if not <hi>moſtly,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s no duty? Your after-inſtances re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain it to the murdering of Chriſt, or ſome great ſin. Then it ſeems we ought to <hi>repent,</hi> (That is, <hi>Change our mind and will, and wiſh we had not done what we did</hi> (which you call the <hi>prime and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſence of Repentance</hi> within a few lines) of <hi>all</hi> ſin; but be <hi>ſorry (in repenting)</hi> only for ſome <hi>great</hi> ſin. But <hi>how great</hi> you tell us not, except the murdering of Chriſt muſt be taken for its <hi>meaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet here you argue from the negative, <hi>a non dicto ad non factum.</hi> There might be great <hi>ſorrow,</hi> where we have it not expreſſed; and where we find the Goſpel Preached, affecting with preſent joy, there might be room enough for ſorrow <hi>afterward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you go on to fortifie this notion from 2 Cor. 7. 9, &amp; 10. <hi>I rejoyce not that ye were made ſorry, but that ye ſorrowed to Repentance; for godly ſorrow worketh Repentance to Salvation, not to be repented of;</hi> You then demand, <hi>Is the ſence godly ſorrow worketh, godly ſorrow? I</hi> anſwer no: and yet you are never the nearer your end; for one <hi>part</hi> of Repentance may very well contribute to another. And this other part, <hi>Emendation,</hi> being the more excellent part, may very well take the denomination of the whole. <hi>Conviction</hi> is not <hi>Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> yet Converſion <hi>includes</hi> Conviction; not only as an inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble adjunct, but alſo as an eſſential part. And if it ſhould be ſaid, Conviction <hi>worketh</hi> Converſion to life; this would not conclude, that Converſion doth not <hi>include</hi> Conviction. This is ſpoken of Repentance in <hi>this</hi> life, to which you have led me by going out of the way.</p>
               <p>But to tell you my thoughts of Repentance of Souls in heaven, <hi>I</hi> am of opinion, that there is <hi>none there: I</hi> take Repentance, and ſo do <hi>you,</hi> to conſiſt in its <hi>primary principal</hi> parts, in the <hi>change</hi> of the Underſtanding and <hi>Will;</hi> and this differs ſo little from the ſence of the word <hi>Converſion,</hi> as is hardly if at all <hi>diſtinguiſhable.</hi> It may be ſaid of the Saints in heaven, that they are <hi>Converted,</hi> but not that there is any Converſion <hi>there:</hi> The like of Repentance. Becauſe the acts of Converſion and Repentance are <hi>in via,</hi> and may properly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106050:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>be called the <hi>tranſitus</hi> or paſſage of the Soul, from all the corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of nature, to <hi>Conſummate</hi> grace, which is not attained in <hi>this</hi> life. But when Grace is <hi>Conſummate;</hi> the work of Repentance and Converſion is over, becauſe there is no more ſin to Convert or <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent from.</hi> And you allow all that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to fortifie this ſence; in your ſaying p. 24. to prove, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> for ſin is not alway a neceſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary adjunct of Repentance, Heb. 6 &amp; 1. <hi>It is not called Repentance</hi> for <hi>dead works, but</hi> from <hi>dead works;</hi> if this will ſerve your turn, to ſhut out <hi>ſorrow</hi> from Repentance here, it will ſerve mine much more to ſhut Repentance out of heaven; for <hi>there</hi> can be no repenting <hi>from</hi> dead works, ſo as to make any change after they are lodged in that perfect ſtate, and have no dead works to repent <hi>from.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> conclude with a few paſſages of <hi>your</hi> own, which makes you ſeem ſo <hi>generous,</hi> as to <hi>give</hi> freely; though you will hardly yield to have the ſame things <hi>forced</hi> from you. <hi>But we find no talk in Scripture of any in heaven</hi> repenting <hi>but God:</hi> No wonder; <hi>how little hath God told us of the particular ſtate and action of ſeparated Souls, before the Reſurrection; When it pleaſeth God ſo</hi> ſparingly <hi>to mention their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate, (yea, and their Immortality in the Old Teſtament) ſhall we</hi> feign <hi>that he muſt tell us of all their thoughts?</hi> Page 25. But your laſt and beſt words on this argument are, <hi>I only hence conclude, that we muſt not take on us to know more than we do of ſeparate Souls, nor to make a meaſure, or manner of bleſſedneſs for them of our own</hi> heads, <hi>nor to apply every Text to them that is ſpoken of the ſtate after the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. There is enough beſides to feaſt our joyful hopes.</hi> Anſw.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Cur in Theatrum Cato ſevere yeniſti?</l>
                  <l>An ideo tantum veneras ut exires?</l>
               </q>
               <p>You ſeem to have faln out, that we might ſhake hands at Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation. You have here (if we may take your ſence by your words) <hi>repented</hi> of your <hi>undoubted</hi> repentance and diſpleaſure to the Saints in heaven; for to ſay there is ſuch things there, is to <hi>feign</hi> to our ſelves, and of our own heads; for of theſe the Scripture <hi>no</hi> where ſpeaks. I thought we ſhould meet at Hedge or Style. It's better parting in ſan Weather then in a <hi>Storm.</hi> And therefore</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106050:25"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
